<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Announcement | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/announcement/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-25T14:37:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog Topics]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/blog-topics/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-22T17:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/blog-topics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was inspired by <a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/platform-book-review/">Michael Hyatt's book, Platform,</a> to start writing this blog.  As he suggested, I just started writing.  But also as he suggested, I've been percolating over what my blog topics will be.  I've just been writing for several weeks.  I've finally settled in on a number of categories that will help me focus a bit.  But each are plenty broad to be able to write on most any and all things related to software.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm1.staticflickr.com/1/2612308_456907e315_z.jpg" alt="Categories" />
http://flic.kr/p/eoxN</p>

<!--more-->


<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/code/">Code</a></h2>

<p>I'm a coder.  This is probably my favorite category.  This is what I wake up in the morning and do.  Posts in this category will be heavy on the code snippets.  They will sometimes link to demos.  These will be the most technical of the posts</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/software-design/">Design</a></h2>

<p>I have a desire to use and expand my design skills.  I'll probably never commit enough time to really be a fantastic designer like many that I know, but here I'll post my own feeble designs and talk about all things having to do with look and feel and user experience.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/productivity/">Productivity</a></h2>

<p>Software is such a malleable medium.  It is an art in many ways.  Thus there are many ways to make it happen.  Some methods work better for others.  Some processes improve upon those of the past.  Some ways are better than others to make a team work well.  Ideas similar to these will be posted here.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/reviews/">Reviews</a></h2>

<p>The world of software and technology is rich with resources and activity.  With so much to choose from, sometimes its helpful to have a suggestion or two on where to (or not to) focus some time and energy.  Software, books, and conferences are subjects we've seen so far.  The reviews are worth the price of admission.  Get them here.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/announcement/">Announcements</a></h2>

<p>Public service announcements will include things about me or the blog in particular that are informational but not to any end.  This post fits in this category.  Where a full review is not offered, tidbits about the software world in general might fit here.</p>

<h2>Blog Topics</h2>

<p>It turns out that it's somewhat hard to choose topics to write about on one's blog.  At least it is for me.  The tech world is changing quickly.  I'm one that likes to change it and and change with it.  So, these topics may evolve.  They seem broad enough to continue to be applicable.</p>

<p>If you were to choose my next post, which category would it fit into?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Chose a WordPress Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/why-i-chose-a-wordpress-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-25T16:49:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/why-i-chose-a-wordpress-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some might ask why a guy who loves his life of code would choose WordPress as the framework for one of his websites. Well, I chose a WordPress blog. I almost didn't. It's been a long time coming. It's early in the game, but I think it was a good choice.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Z9HMK.jpg" alt="WordPress T-Shirt" />
http://flic.kr/p/6FFZMy</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Why I wouldn't choose WordPress blog</h2>

<p>I only had one job about 7 years back that consisted of mostly PHP. The job was great for many reasons. PHP wasn't the highlight. We did some cool stuff with it. At the time, it was all right. Since, I have coded full time in Java, Python, XQuery, or JavaScript. I would count each as <strong>more</strong> enjoyable than PHP.</p>

<p>Secondly, I'm a coder. I love to build stuff. Custom software is way more fun than boxed software. WordPress is something that is literally accessible to anyone that's just computer savvy. I'm not breaking new ground on WordPress.</p>

<h2>An insightful article</h2>

<p>A week or so ago, I ran into an article on a site called "Virtuous Code". That site name was cool enough. The article was typed ("penned" is such a cooler word) by Avdi Grimm and is named <a href="http://devblog.avdi.org/2012/08/09/why-wordpress/">"Why WordPress"</a>. I was caught off guard by how well it described my personal predicament.</p>

<h2>Why I chose a WordPress blog</h2>

<p>When I read Avid's article, I realized that the reasons I, as a coder, had been avoiding WordPress were the very reasons I should embrace it:</p>

<ol>
<li>As a coder, my tendency to jump into the internals and start toying around is strong. This hinders my writing ability. It competes for my time. Writing is something that I really want to do more of. By choosing a package that's tied up with a bow will encourage me to just use it instead of over-customize it. And since the innards of the package is a language that I don't want to devote a ton of my time to, I'm even less inclined to customize it.</li>
<li>PHP and WordPress are, in a way, like JavaScript -- they're everwhere, and everyone is using them. This means that probably just about everything that I could imagine wanting (ok, I'll probably come up with something innane) on a blog has already been built. I don't need to reinvent it.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Driven to the edge</h2>

<p>So, I made the jump. I just downloaded the latest <a href="http:://wordpress.org">WordPress.org</a> package. I ran Apache on my local box and pointed my browser to <code>localhost:8888</code>. I was presented with the pleasant admin UI. I chose a new theme. It installed in place. It was a 2-click ordeal. I chose a few plugins to replace default functionality and add a bit more. I was pleasantly surprised by the smoothness of it all.</p>

<p>At the point I was getting the blog looking nice and doing what I wanted, did I care that the thing was written in PHP? No. I saw it just once when setting up my DB connection. I did cringe slightly upon seeing some <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/language.variables.superglobals.php">super globals</a> again (<code>$_SERVER</code>), but I hastily committed the change and deployed the app.</p>

<p>We'll see if I continue to love it, but so far, so good. My fellow coders, I ask: Is my reasoning sound?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
