<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: erb | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/erb/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-24T11:07:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multiple Yields in an ERB Template]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/multiple-yields-in-erb-template/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-08T07:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/multiple-yields-in-erb-template</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you setup a new Rails project, you'll have a single layout file which has a single default <code>yield</code> block.  This will soon be inadequate, and you'll want another.  Here's how to setup multiple <code>yield</code> blocks per ERB template.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/YqUKEfw.png" alt="Multiple ERB yields" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Layout File</h2>

<p>By default, Rails will create a file at:</p>

<p><code>
app/views/layouts/application.html.erb
</code></p>

<p>In this file, there will be a default <code>yield</code> block similar to this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
&lt;%= yield %&gt;
</code></p>

<p>It has no name.  It's just the default place for templates that use this layout file to put their content.</p>

<p>We can create new <code>yield</code> blocks.  We'll have to give them a distinguishing name.  They look about the same.  If I wanted to create a new <code>yield</code> block where, for instance, alerts could be displayed if the child template had them, I could put this in my layout file:</p>

<p><code>ruby
&lt;%= yield(:alert) %&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Now I would just need something to go in it.</p>

<h2>Child Templates</h2>

<p>A child template that uses the <code>application.html.erb</code> layout file can just start blasting out markup that will go into the default <code>yield</code> block.  This will usually be the main content.  But in our example, there might be more focused content such as alerts that we want to display in a separate area.  Thus, our template could potentially look like this:</p>

<p>```erb</p>

<h1>My main content</h1>


<p>Bacon ipsum…<p>

<% content_for :alert do %>
  <div class="alert alert-success">
    You created multiple yield blocks!
  </div>
<% end %>
```

Throw down a `content_for` block, matching the name of the `yield` block in your layout file, and you're set.  Order does not matter.  Your specific `content_for` blocks can come before, after, or in the middle of your main content.  Easy as Ruby pie.

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
