<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blog | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-25T11:13:26-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress vs. WordPress]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/octopress-vs-wordpress/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-12T16:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/octopress-vs-wordpress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Why would one choose Octopress over WordPress?  What are the pros and cons?  I've recently implemented a blog -- this blog -- in WordPress.  It was a difficult decision for me.  At the time, I looked at Octopress, but I was jazzed by the success of others on WordPress, and I wanted to try it out.  I'm glad that I did try it out, but now I'm glad that I've switched to Octopress.  Here's why.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/uACBn.jpg" alt="Octopress" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Just Posts</h2>

<p>Octopress is so dead simple, it just makes sense.  The post is a file in a folder.  I edit it in my current favorite MarkDown editor, <a href="http://mouapp.com/">Mou</a>.  The workflow is thus very easy.  I'm not transferring my post which I wrote offline to a web interface only available online.</p>

<h2>Nerd Cred</h2>

<p>Nerd cred or geek cred?  I don't know, but Octopress bumps it right up.  As it says, it's a "blogging framework for hackers".  Given that I'm a creator of software and that's the main topic of my blog, it seems fitting, doesn't it.  Plenty of coders have WordPress sites, I suppose.  Still, I didn't feel super awesome about running a WordPress PHP site as my home base.</p>

<h2>Performance</h2>

<p>The whole idea of a generated static site seems genius.  It's blazing fast.  I'm on Heroku.  Currently, my site experiences very low volume traffic.  With one dyno, when the site goes without traffic for a certain amount of time, Heroku will power down the dyno.  WordPress takes a fair bit to come back up on the first request after that.  Octopress, no problem.  Pops back like it was never gone.  And why not?  There's really nothing to spin up.</p>

<h2>No Reinvention</h2>

<p>I landed on Octopress for one of the same reasons I initially chose WordPress for this new blog.  It is a ready-made blogging platform.  I don't need to reinvent the wheel.  It works, and it works well.</p>

<h2>A Bit of Customization</h2>

<p>I chose WordPress for the blog because I wanted to write blog posts, not tinker with the innards of the site.  (I do that plenty elsewhere.)  But it turns out that I couldn't quite bare just using an out-of-the-box theme.  I literally needed to add my own flair and customizations.  I still want to keep that to a minimum.  Octopress' classic theme (the only one?) is fantastic -- clean and crisp.  When I want to make a few changes, it's a much more straight-forward task to find the place that needs editing and get it done.</p>

<h2>Ruby</h2>

<p>I've hardly done any Ruby.  Octopress is an easy little touch of Ruby.  I don't have to mess with it unless I want to.  Ruby is much more appealing to me than PHP.</p>

<h2>Plugin Pluses</h2>

<p>When I chose WordPress, I figured that if there was any feature that I desired, there was probably already a plugin for it.  And that turned out to be true.  Octopress certainly <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/wiki/3rd-party-plugins">has fewer options</a>.  But on the whole, I think they cater well to the coder crowd.</p>

<h2>For Now</h2>

<p>So, for now, I'm on Octopress.  It's nice to think that my data is just a folder of files that I could really recreate anywhere.  So, we'll see how long this lasts.  So far, it's a blogging platform for this hacker, and I'm liking it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog Topics]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/blog-topics/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-22T17:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/blog-topics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was inspired by <a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/platform-book-review/">Michael Hyatt's book, Platform,</a> to start writing this blog.  As he suggested, I just started writing.  But also as he suggested, I've been percolating over what my blog topics will be.  I've just been writing for several weeks.  I've finally settled in on a number of categories that will help me focus a bit.  But each are plenty broad to be able to write on most any and all things related to software.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm1.staticflickr.com/1/2612308_456907e315_z.jpg" alt="Categories" />
http://flic.kr/p/eoxN</p>

<!--more-->


<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/code/">Code</a></h2>

<p>I'm a coder.  This is probably my favorite category.  This is what I wake up in the morning and do.  Posts in this category will be heavy on the code snippets.  They will sometimes link to demos.  These will be the most technical of the posts</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/software-design/">Design</a></h2>

<p>I have a desire to use and expand my design skills.  I'll probably never commit enough time to really be a fantastic designer like many that I know, but here I'll post my own feeble designs and talk about all things having to do with look and feel and user experience.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/productivity/">Productivity</a></h2>

<p>Software is such a malleable medium.  It is an art in many ways.  Thus there are many ways to make it happen.  Some methods work better for others.  Some processes improve upon those of the past.  Some ways are better than others to make a team work well.  Ideas similar to these will be posted here.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/reviews/">Reviews</a></h2>

<p>The world of software and technology is rich with resources and activity.  With so much to choose from, sometimes its helpful to have a suggestion or two on where to (or not to) focus some time and energy.  Software, books, and conferences are subjects we've seen so far.  The reviews are worth the price of admission.  Get them here.</p>

<h2><a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/category/announcement/">Announcements</a></h2>

<p>Public service announcements will include things about me or the blog in particular that are informational but not to any end.  This post fits in this category.  Where a full review is not offered, tidbits about the software world in general might fit here.</p>

<h2>Blog Topics</h2>

<p>It turns out that it's somewhat hard to choose topics to write about on one's blog.  At least it is for me.  The tech world is changing quickly.  I'm one that likes to change it and and change with it.  So, these topics may evolve.  They seem broad enough to continue to be applicable.</p>

<p>If you were to choose my next post, which category would it fit into?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I Chose a WordPress Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/why-i-chose-a-wordpress-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-25T16:49:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/why-i-chose-a-wordpress-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some might ask why a guy who loves his life of code would choose WordPress as the framework for one of his websites. Well, I chose a WordPress blog. I almost didn't. It's been a long time coming. It's early in the game, but I think it was a good choice.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Z9HMK.jpg" alt="WordPress T-Shirt" />
http://flic.kr/p/6FFZMy</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Why I wouldn't choose WordPress blog</h2>

<p>I only had one job about 7 years back that consisted of mostly PHP. The job was great for many reasons. PHP wasn't the highlight. We did some cool stuff with it. At the time, it was all right. Since, I have coded full time in Java, Python, XQuery, or JavaScript. I would count each as <strong>more</strong> enjoyable than PHP.</p>

<p>Secondly, I'm a coder. I love to build stuff. Custom software is way more fun than boxed software. WordPress is something that is literally accessible to anyone that's just computer savvy. I'm not breaking new ground on WordPress.</p>

<h2>An insightful article</h2>

<p>A week or so ago, I ran into an article on a site called "Virtuous Code". That site name was cool enough. The article was typed ("penned" is such a cooler word) by Avdi Grimm and is named <a href="http://devblog.avdi.org/2012/08/09/why-wordpress/">"Why WordPress"</a>. I was caught off guard by how well it described my personal predicament.</p>

<h2>Why I chose a WordPress blog</h2>

<p>When I read Avid's article, I realized that the reasons I, as a coder, had been avoiding WordPress were the very reasons I should embrace it:</p>

<ol>
<li>As a coder, my tendency to jump into the internals and start toying around is strong. This hinders my writing ability. It competes for my time. Writing is something that I really want to do more of. By choosing a package that's tied up with a bow will encourage me to just use it instead of over-customize it. And since the innards of the package is a language that I don't want to devote a ton of my time to, I'm even less inclined to customize it.</li>
<li>PHP and WordPress are, in a way, like JavaScript -- they're everwhere, and everyone is using them. This means that probably just about everything that I could imagine wanting (ok, I'll probably come up with something innane) on a blog has already been built. I don't need to reinvent it.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Driven to the edge</h2>

<p>So, I made the jump. I just downloaded the latest <a href="http:://wordpress.org">WordPress.org</a> package. I ran Apache on my local box and pointed my browser to <code>localhost:8888</code>. I was presented with the pleasant admin UI. I chose a new theme. It installed in place. It was a 2-click ordeal. I chose a few plugins to replace default functionality and add a bit more. I was pleasantly surprised by the smoothness of it all.</p>

<p>At the point I was getting the blog looking nice and doing what I wanted, did I care that the thing was written in PHP? No. I saw it just once when setting up my DB connection. I did cringe slightly upon seeing some <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/language.variables.superglobals.php">super globals</a> again (<code>$_SERVER</code>), but I hastily committed the change and deployed the app.</p>

<p>We'll see if I continue to love it, but so far, so good. My fellow coders, I ask: Is my reasoning sound?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review for Platform]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/book-review-for-platform/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-25T16:46:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/book-review-for-platform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do you inform people of your next big idea? How do you motivate others to continue listening to you once you have their attention? In the age of the Internet, there are countless competitors in almost every space. To differentiate yourself, you'll need to create something truly amazing. But that's not enough. Get that product or service into the public eye, and engage the masses to take a look and spread the good word. Michael Hyatt shares how to build the <em>platform</em> upon which this process will happen.</p>

<p><img src="http://c.michaelhyatt.com/banners/platform/728x901.png" alt="Just over that rise" />
http://michaelhyatt.com/platform</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Is this book for you?</h2>

<p>Michael Hyatt's book, "<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Platform-Get-Noticed-Noisy-World/dp/159555503X">Platform - Get Noticed in a Noisy World</a>" is an impressive book. As the books second subtitle says, it's "a step-by-step guide for anyone with something to say or sell". As it turns out, anyone with a product, service, or idea fits in this category.</p>

<h2>The Gist of Platform</h2>

<p>His strategy, and book, is broken into 5 sequential areas:</p>

<ol>
<li>Start with Wow</li>
<li>Prepare to Launch</li>
<li>Build Your Home Base</li>
<li>Expand Your Reach</li>
<li>Engage Your Tribe</li>
</ol>


<h2>The importance of a blog</h2>

<p>The doesn't get too much into product creation. My favorite chapter on that topic was chapter 2, "Bake in the Wow". It contained great "wow" checklist items that will be insightful for your own product creation.</p>

<p>Michael's strategy centers around a blog, or as he calls it, a "home base". This is the channel you control. You control the content, the format, the distribution, the readership, etc. He fills most of the book with this advice. This is where your product or service happens. This is where you direct everyone.</p>

<p>The advice is specific: titles, lengths of posts, frequency of writing, language, policies, and more is covered. He also gives ample treatment to the effective use of Twitter. Throughout, I was impressed with his sharing of specific tools or websites that are helpful.</p>

<h2>One small, perhaps fundamental beef</h2>

<p>To me, section 2, "Prepare to Launch", comes before section 1, "Start with Wow". Why? Because you really have to envision your product before you create it. What is the product you'll create? What is the exact problem you are trying to solve? Who is your target market? How will you distribute your service?</p>

<p>As Michael says in chapter 11 on creating an elevator pitch: You must first achieve clarity yourself before you can spread the message to others. Would this not come before potentially time/cost-intensive creation of your product? Both sections are fantastic, by the way.</p>

<h2>Blog-like Style</h2>

<p>Mike covers a lot of ground in this book. The information is immediately relevant to anyone (everyone) who wants (needs) an Internet presence. The read is quick and easy with short chapters that get right to the point (essentially a blog post per chapter). The core information close to the surface with little cruft. The voice is conversational and compelling as Mike tells his own story of how he has developed a following online.</p>

<p>It's no wonder that his blog has garnered thousands of followers -- the book was a good read with great content for creating a strong online presence. Or was it?  It was enough to help motivate me to start this blog.  Did you find it helpful/original?</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
