<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: teams | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/teams/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-05T13:38:38-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make Your Project Fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/make-your-project-fun/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-06T07:16:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/make-your-project-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You work every day.  It's a part of life.  It's a good part of life, and you have the power to make it better.  Ever since you were  young child, you knew what the magic ingredient was: fun!</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ACkhQQK.jpg" alt="Fun" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Making software is a creative endeavor.  It allows situations for lots of free thinking.  It comes with the satisfaction of creating something from nothing.  It allows stretching of your cognitive ability.  This is all made more enjoyable by having a mental affinity for fun.</p>

<p>Fun people create fun work.  Fun people are fun to work with.  It's fun to look at fun people's work.  Fun, fun, fun.  [We can't keep doing this, Bob.]</p>

<p>So look for ways to make your project fun.  Here are a few ideas.</p>

<h2>404 Page</h2>

<p>I love the creative outlet that 404 pages have become.  There are blogs of the "Top 25 Funniest 404 Pages" and the like.  It is now common to have companies try to make the most uncommon of "page not found" pages.  You look up to the sites that take the time to make a witty 404 page.  Make one yourself.  If your brand isn't funny (maybe it should be!), at least flirt with funny and push the envelope on happy as much as you can -- and then one step more.</p>

<p>Here's a 404 page that our team made before the designers had come to a conclusion on a recent project.  It's still there.  It's one of my favorite additions to the site.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/HobT77O.png" alt="Doge 404" /></p>

<p>You'll find that fun projects also present opportunities to do things that you wouldn't usually otherwise do.  For instance, I spent half an hour drawing vectorized Doge -- again, a favorite experience in my memory.</p>

<h2>Animate Things</h2>

<p>I am drawn to almost any page that includes some sort of data visualization.  I love making those pages.  Part of the reason is that there's always room to add a bit of your own flair to the thing.  Designers rarely get to the point where they start defining animations, and I love animations, so I get to experiment with what I like and fill that in later.  And animation is usually impressive to users later, so the payoff is nice.</p>

<p>Here is a fun animation of a gauge that I made for a project that was meant to evoke a car engine revving at startup:</p>

<p data-height="279" data-theme-id="1749" data-slug-hash="eloGk" data-default-tab="result" data-user="jaketrent" data-preview="true" class="codepen">See the Pen <a href="http://codepen.io/jaketrent/pen/eloGk/">D3 Gauge</a> by Jake Trent (<a href="http://codepen.io/jaketrent">@jaketrent</a>) on <a href="http://codepen.io">CodePen</a>.</p>


<script async src="http://jaketrent.com//assets.codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js"></script>


<h2>Don't Use the Prebuilt</h2>

<p>At this point in the UI design timeline, there are many, many prebuilt widgets for today's current look that you can just slap on the page.  You might get done early, but it won't look original.  Your site will just look like many, many other sites.  In my opinion, this is an unwelcome trend in web and mobile app design today -- everything seems to be converging.  But this just makes original designs all the more special and appreciated.</p>

<p>In a recent project, I could have thrown in any of a host of prebuilt loading spinners, but I wanted to do something different and quirky.  We had charts that relied on async data coming from a server, so we had the UI show a chart loading state.  Here's what I came up with for the line chart:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5gCGnzk.gif" alt="Line chart loading" /></p>

<p>It's meant to evoke a heart monitor.  And for the bar chart:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/7WetiZ8.gif" alt="Bar chart loading" /></p>

<p>I was going to speed it up to make it more equalizer-ish, but then slowed it down so-as to be less busy.  Feel free to <a href="https://github.com/jaketrent/react-chart-loading">download and use it</a> yourself.</p>

<h2>Have Some Fun Team Spirit</h2>

<p>I've previously already mentioned my love for team and project <a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/in-favor-codenames/">codenames</a>.  You should get one, and it should come from a universe of thought that's original or exciting and fun to you.  This is to please you and your team, not anyone else.  Make T-shirts.  I've thought about this often, but have never produced my own, so this suggestion is for me.  For one of my teams, I even picked a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0gC7bmIDQjY">theme song, Moliendo café,</a> to go with our team code name, Ranchero.  Those are happy memories of good times.</p>

<p>Make a logo.  Choose something that will be fun.  Imagine it as a sticker on the back of a laptop lid.  Will in be awesome there?  When measured in logos, the coolest frontend web framework available today is <a href="http://emberjs.com/">Ember</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/dwho9tp.png" alt="Ember logo" /></p>

<p>When measured in logos, the coolest tech conference of the past year was <a href="http://www.reactrally.com/">React Rally</a>:</p>

<p><img src="https://d13yacurqjgara.cloudfront.net/users/700730/screenshots/2171778/evilsquid_1x.png" alt="React Rally logo" /></p>

<p>Who doesn't think a bespectacled (Tom) hamster or a nuclear-powered squid aren't the funnest logos one could plaster on his laptop?  We need more mascots.</p>

<p>In short, have fun.  Don't wait for your project to become fun.  Make it fun.  Make your project fun.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working More Might Not Help Our Team]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/work-more-might-not-help/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-18T16:50:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/work-more-might-not-help</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some have surmised that working more will help their team.  It may.  It may not.  It depends.  Here's just one collection of thoughts on how working significantly <em>more</em> than the <em>rest</em> of our team might not help and may actually hinder.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/xRlumnh.jpg" alt="Rise together as a team" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>What is "More"?</h2>

<p>Working "more" than the team may mean many things.  Perhaps it means <em>more time</em> -- more time in the office, more time in certain worthy activities.  Perhaps it means <em>more skill</em> -- more productive, better at the things I care about.  Perhaps it means <em>more quality</em> -- produce better work at better rates.  Perhaps it means <em>more commitment</em> -- more focus, more sense of purpose, more of an innate sense of urgency.</p>

<p>"More", for purposes of these thoughts also means <em>unevenly</em> more -- as in one person or subset of the team doing significantly more than the rest of the team.  I won't address it further here, but I think that generally if the whole team can do <em>more together</em>, within their capabilities, teams will get more better [sic].</p>

<h2>Carrying the Burden of the Team</h2>

<p>When we work significantly more than others, it can be easy to feel like we're carrying the brunt of the workload of the team.  The team has work to do, and we're doing the most of it.  We come in first.  We leave last.  Others on the team come and go in between.</p>

<p>If we were to work similar hours to the reset of the team, we'd be less likely to feel that we were unduly burdened.  If we looked less at when people were in their seats, we'd feel less like a bean-counting manager.  We'd allow others to make their own time management choices.  We'd allow ourselves to focus more on our purpose for being on the team.</p>

<h4>What Can We Do?</h4>

<p>Each situation likely requires thought and consideration of the team and those involved.  But here are some ideas on how we might overcome issues of uneven team contribution.</p>

<ul>
<li>If we must count, count hours less, count contribution more.  Hard.</li>
<li>Focus on ourselves.  Put expectations on ourselves.  We can control those things.</li>
<li>Life's never fair.  Sometimes we <em>do</em> carry more burden.  Sometimes we are carried.</li>
<li>Share what we're doing on the team.  Transparency may help dispel myth.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Rise Together</h2>

<p>Part of our purpose for being on the team is to help the <em>entire</em> team be better.  If the team completes the work together and we need every person on the team, sometimes we need to specifically focus on helping our team grow in capability, focus, happiness, quality, output, or whatever it is that we feel the team is lacking.</p>

<p>We may not really be addressing the issue that needs addressed -- whether a real challenge of the team or something we have conjured in our mind -- by just hammering out more work.  If we take this course of just pressing on with greater speed, time commitment, and effort, we may actually make the problem worse, encouraging ourselves to believe more deeply that we are carrying the weight of the team.</p>

<h4>What Can We Do?</h4>

<ul>
<li>Consider how we might lift the total capability of the team.</li>
<li>Be constructive and helpful to others.  In order to get here, we need to stop feeling sorry for ourselves.</li>
<li>Sometimes we might slow down and invest in the team itself.</li>
</ul>


<h2>False Heroism</h2>

<p>Once we are working significantly more than the rest of the team, we can come to believe that the team relies on us above all others.  We may attract praise and be singled out.  This may lead us to do more of the thing -- the potentially unhealthy thing -- that we're doing in order to attract more praise.</p>

<p>Soon, to keep up this pattern of addictive praise incoming, we may begin to create more situations where we can swoop in, do significantly more than others and hopefully be held up as an example of adoration for others to aspire to.  This is a cycle that makes things worse.</p>

<p>Lifting ourselves above our teammates leads to rampant comparison.  We cultivate pride in ourselves.  We start to feel like we need to prove our continuing contribution.  We speak up about what we individually have done to save and push forward our projects.  We use a lot of "I..."-subject phrases.  We are quick to point out after-hours or extended contributions.  The focus becomes me instead of the team.  The product becomes my own personal activities instead of the team output.</p>

<h4>What Can We Do?</h4>

<ul>
<li>Make comparisons for the purpose of helping and filling the deficit of others.</li>
<li>See our strengths as opportunities to help others weak in those areas, not a chance to shine above them.</li>
<li>Be judicious in public praise.  We get more of the thing we praise.  Praise can have side effects.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Stories We Tell Ourselves</h2>

<p>When we're so focused on ourselves, it's easy to be very out of touch with others.  We're often uncomfortable in approaching others about our shared contribution because, of course, we believe that we're doing so much than the rest of the group and are likely upset in some ways with the team.</p>

<p>So we're left to ourselves.  We tell ourselves stories about why the rest of the team just can't or won't keep up.  We create reasons in our mind to explain the source of their lesser commitment.  Some of it actually might be true, but the story is left to us to tell, and it's likely embellished and unfair.</p>

<h4>What Can We Do?</h4>

<ul>
<li>Notice when we're telling ourselves things in our mind that we don't actually know are true.  Practice distinguishing actual fact from yet-unproved fact.</li>
<li>Give people the benefit of the doubt.  Trust in usually-good intentions.</li>
<li>Talk with others.  Tell them our concerns.  Hear their perspective.  We'll probably be surprised with new appreciation.</li>
</ul>


<h2>It is a "We" Problem</h2>

<p>I use "we" in this article because I believe we all can suffer at different times and degrees from this malady.  We value what we bring to the table, and we should.  It's the comparison with our teammates that's the problem.  Pride is universal.</p>

<p>I also use "we" because this problem and its children problems are issues that we, <em>as a team</em>, need to help one another overcome.  I also believe that every one of us has the ability, hopefully with the help of help of our concerned teammates, to overcome this and other problems that keep us from being better teams.</p>

<h2>Great Teams Aren't Perfect</h2>

<p>I hope everyone has some number of opportunities to work with great teams.  It's an awesome feeling to feel united in a purpose.  It's awesome to feel supported by others around us.  It's awesome to see our efforts magnified in a greater whole.</p>

<p>Even great teams have troubles.  It's never going to be perfect.  Don't lose heart.  Great teams will be able to have patience, see each other as human beings doing their best, and find a way to make it work and work well.</p>

<p>I think some of this has felt familiar as we've read through it together.  We are all still growing on our teams.  What have you done to make your teams work better together and not make any one person feel overburdened?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
