<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: nodejs | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/nodejs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-23T08:06:38-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Access NodeJs App on Xip.io]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/nodejs-app-on-xipio/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-23T07:22:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/nodejs-app-on-xipio</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Xip.io is a DNS wildcard domain that was initially created for use on Ruby projects.  But its application is desirable across platforms.  Recently, I wanted to use Xip.io on a NodeJs project.  It was easy to make happen.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/M0kYA.jpg" alt="xip.io" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Install Pow and Powder</h2>

<p>Pow is a development server that uses Xip.io.  Powder is a cli that makes working with Pow even easier.  To start, make sure that <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/">Ruby</a> is setup with <a href="http://rubygems.org">Rubygems</a> in your environment.  Then install Pow.  They have a short little install script you can run, as <a href="http://pow.cx/">referenced on the Pow site</a>.</p>

<p>Then install Powder:</p>

<p><code>
gem install powder
</code></p>

<h2>Proxy your NodeJs app</h2>

<p>Pow only knows how to handle Rack apps, so we have to create one to be loaded into Pow.  Since we're writing the guts of our app on another platform -- in this case, Node -- we'll just create a proxy Rack app.</p>

<p>I found a bit of <a href="https://github.com/linjunpop/node-with-pow">proxy app code</a>, which you should save in your project root as <code>config.ru</code>, and which I paste here:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'><span class="nb">require</span> <span class="s2">&quot;net/http&quot;</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">&lt;p&gt;class ProxyApp</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="sr">  def call(env)&lt;/</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="k">begin</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">request</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Rack</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="no">Request</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">env</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">headers</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">{}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">env</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">each</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">value</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">key</span> <span class="o">=~</span> <span class="sr">/^http_(.*)/i</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">headers</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="vg">$1</span><span class="o">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">value</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">http</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">Net</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="no">HTTP</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;localhost&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">3000</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="n">http</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">start</span> <span class="k">do</span> <span class="o">|</span><span class="n">http</span><span class="o">|</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">response</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">http</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">send_request</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">request</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">request_method</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">request</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">fullpath</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">request</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">body</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">read</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">headers</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">[</span><span class="n">response</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">code</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">response</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">to_hash</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="n">response</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">body</span><span class="o">]]</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">rescue</span> <span class="no">Errno</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="no">ECONNREFUSED</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">[</span><span class="mi">500</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="p">{},</span> <span class="o">[</span><span class="s2">&quot;Server is down, try $npm start&quot;</span><span class="o">]]</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="sr">/code&gt;&lt;/</span><span class="n">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nb">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">run</span> <span class="no">ProxyApp</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>The only change you might have to make is the port number for your app (line 13).  In this case, I'm using port 3000 for my NodeJs app.</p>

<h2>Link Your App</h2>

<p>Now all we have to do is link our app to Pow.  Powder helps us do this easily.  Go to your project root directory and type:</p>

<p><code>
powder link &lt;project_name&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Now run your app with whatever command starts NodeJs.  It's probably something like this:</p>

<p><code>
node app.js
</code></p>

<p>Now you should be able to access your app via your web browser at <code>http://&lt;project_name&gt;.dev</code>.  One of the great things about Xip.io is that it makes running your local app <a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/run-pow-server-on-vm/">extremely easy from a local Virtual machine</a> as well.  To get the address of your app to use in your VM, type this from your native terminal:</p>

<p><code>
powder open --xip
</code></p>

<p>And copy the resulting URL into your VM web browser.</p>

<p>Ah, the fusion of Node and Ruby is pretty sweet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Https Redirect for Node on Heroku]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/https-redirect-node-heroku/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-26T07:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/https-redirect-node-heroku</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When your app requires users to be using the <code>https</code> protocol to make requests and get responses, it's helpful to have an automatic redirect so the user is always in the right place.  Here's how to do that for a Node Express app on Heroku.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/5rZ8H.png" alt="NodeJs Https Redirect" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Secure Express Requests</h2>

<p>The <a href="http://expressjs.com">Express</a> request object has a bunch of great information.  One of its attributes is <code>secure</code>.  It's a boolean.  Usually, <code>secure == true</code> will mean that you're on <code>https</code>.  When that is not true, you're ready for a redirect.</p>

<p>Unfortunately for apps hosted on Heroku, <code>request.secure</code> will always be false.  The way that Heroku routing works, it will just never be set.</p>

<h2>Heroku Https Header</h2>

<p>Instead, Heroku forwards an http header that allows us to do the same "is secure" test.  On Heroku, <code>request.header('x-forwarded-proto')</code> will contain the actual protocol string (eg, 'http' or 'https').</p>

<h2>Express Middleware SSL Redirect</h2>

<p>If you're using the Express framework on Node, then you have it easy.  There's already a great middleware mechanism for you to send any or all requests through.  If you set your Express app (v3) up like this:</p>

<p><code>coffeescript
app = express()
</code></p>

<p>Then you can use the <code>app.use</code> functionality to specify a middleware.  Since I only have certificates and want the redirect to happen in the production environment, I will likewise wrap this middleware inside <code>app.configure</code> for prod (it inspects <code>NODE_ENV</code> for you).  This redirect will be pretty rudimentary, but it's just that simple, so here it goes:</p>

<p>```coffeescript
app.configure 'production', ->
  app.use forceSsl(req, res, next) -></p>

<pre><code>if req.header 'x-forwarded-proto' != 'https'
  res.redirect "https://#{req.header 'host'}#{req.url}"
else
  next()
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>If it's not <code>https</code> already, redirect the same url on <code>https</code>.  If it is, that's what I want, and you can pass on through my middleware function.  Note that this middleware will protect <em>all</em> urls on the site with an <code>https</code> redirect.  Your middleware could be more selective.  You could even create this as a stacked middleware per route if you wanted.  We could even enhance our middleware to use inspect both the http header <em>and</em> the <code>secure</code> flag.</p>

<p>Heroku threw us a for a minor, unexpected loop, but it was nothing that we couldn't easily code for.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smashing Node Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/smashing-node-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-29T16:51:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/smashing-node-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Node.js is everywhere.  There's a lot of room for people to learn and get into it.  A good starter book is <a href="http://amzn.to/14ttetp">Smashing Node by Guillermo Rauch</a>.  Here's what I thought and what I learned while reading it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/hQTBeAF.jpg" alt="Smashing Node" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Overall</h2>

<p>Overall, I would call Smashing Node an introduction to Node book.  This is a good thing.  It does a nice job of building on itself.  It starts with the JavaScript that everyone knows and advances to the new places that Node allows you to go.  The chapters are incremental.</p>

<p>It's a good length.  This is not a tome that you might pick up in a level 3 dungeon in order to boost your fire magic.  You can read a couple chapters a day and be done in a week.  Thankfully, it's in consumable-sized bits.  Maybe you'll end up boosting your fire magic a bit too.</p>

<p>The book boasts a fair breadth of subjects.  It introduces purely syntax subjects.  It also expands into working examples dealing with real network protocols and database apis.</p>

<h2>Style</h2>

<p>Guirremo has a very easy-to-read, conversational style.  I value this more and more in books -- perhaps even especially in technical books.  It helps me engage.  It helps me read faster and more.  I can read API docs when I need them.  A book should not read like an API doc.</p>

<p>Most subjects in the book were chosen well.  I enjoyed almost all of them.  There always is a bottom of the list, however, and mine ended with the MySQL, HTTP, and TCP chapters.  Knowledge on those subjects is probably good to have, but I had to slog through these chapters.</p>

<p>The code examples were enjoyable because they eventually turned into functional prototypes.  We built a Twitter client, an IRC chat, a social DJ program, and more.  That's pretty cool.  The downside was that the code examples could get a little long.  And with the entire working example, complete with all the npm commands and boilerplate code, sometimes the meaningful bits got a little obscured.  I read the book as a <a href="http://amzn.to/14ttetp">Kindle book</a> on a phone, so the long code snippets probably seemed even longer than they were.</p>

<h2>Highlight Subjects</h2>

<h4>Express Features</h4>

<p>I use <a href="http://expressjs.com/">Express</a> more than any other library in Node.  It's a great HTTP request/response wrapper that makes creating web servers fun and easy.  Even so, this book introduced a number of features of the library that I was previously unaware of.  Generally, I think it helped illuminate for me a lot of the bits of Connect, which functions underneath Express.  Specifically, did you know that you can modify the Express logger to log specific request tokens of your choosing?</p>

<h4>Redis</h4>

<p>There was a great section that took a look at <a href="http://www.mongodb.org/">Mongo</a>, <a href="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a>, and <a href="http://redis.io/">Redis</a>.  I enjoyed the chapter on Redis the most.  This is probaby somewhat because I have the most to learn in Redis and have used it the least.  I was also impressed at the ease with which Guirremo layed out a simple social graph using the Redis API.  The chosen tools, Node and Redis, made it simple, short, and elegant.</p>

<p>Try writing many of the code examples in this book in Java and printing them on dead trees.  You'll need a bigger backpack.</p>

<h4>Testing</h4>

<p>I enjoyed the fact that testing was even mentioned.  A few testing styles and frameworks were introduced.  It was enjoyable but very light.  It would be cool to see a more thorough treatment, perhaps with applicable tests worked into the examples throughout the book.</p>

<p>In this same vein, I think the book did an ok job at addressing the subject of error handling.  I think this book and other Node resources and educators should focus more on this issue.  It is, after all, more important in Node's single-threaded environment than on most platforms.</p>

<h4>Web Sockets</h4>

<p>I had only previously done web sockets via <a href="http://socket.io/">Socket.IO</a>, a web socket wrapper written by the author of the book.  It was good to see vanilla web sockets in action so I could better understand the technology, its limitations, and be grateful for the great libraries that help it be more useful and easy to use.</p>

<h4>Great Libraries</h4>

<p>The booked worked in usages of some great libraries throughout the coding examples.  As mentioned, <a href="http://socket.io/">Socket.IO</a> is a great web socket wrapper.  <a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/superagent">Superagent</a> is a great higher-level request API.  <a href="http://visionmedia.github.com/mocha/">Mocha</a> is a fantastic test framework.  And <a href="http://mongoosejs.com/">Mongoose</a> provides a nice model layer on top of the native MongoDb calls.</p>

<p>So, what are you waiting for?  Go learn Node!  Use this book to help you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Make a Pinterest Webservice]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/how-to-make-pinterest-webservice/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-18T07:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/how-to-make-pinterest-webservice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pinterest currently does not have an official webservice API.  It seems kind of crazy in this day and age.  They really should have one.  I can't think what the business reasons might be for not having one.</p>

<p>They've not had one for long enough that it's high time we write our own.  It'll be surprisingly easy with a few choice tools</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/7cv9d.png" alt="Pinterest API" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Webservice API on NodeJs</h2>

<p><a href="http://nodejs.org/">NodeJs</a> is just a fun platform to write IO-heavy applications for the web.  We're going to write a quick <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer">RESTful</a> endpoint using the <a href="http://expressjs.com/">Express</a> library that allows us to consume real Pinterest content that's not available via a pre-existing service.</p>

<h4>Screen Scrape Pinterest</h4>

<p>Given no API, we're left to our own devices.  The data for Pinterest is only exposed via the UI on the website.  We're going to have our service visit that UI and grab the data that we need as a user of a web browser would see it.  This is screen scraping.  There a lot of downsides here, but we wouldn't be trying it if there was an API already.</p>

<p>One down side is that our service will be brittle.  If Pinterest ever changes the layout of the page, our service won't be able to bring back the right data.  Our solution will be simple, so it'll be easy to update, but this should be a red flag not to do anything mission critical via screen scraping unless you're giving it your full attention.</p>

<p>Another down side might be speed.  Screen scraping a UI is not the fastest way to get data.  We'll try and help mitigate this with the fastest tools that we have.  NodeJs is a blasted fast web server.  A library called <a href="https://github.com/MatthewMueller/cheerio">cheerio</a> is supposedly best-in-class for screen scraping (advertised as 8x faster than <a href="https://github.com/tmpvar/jsdom">jsdom</a>).</p>

<h4>Caching</h4>

<p>To make this retrieval even faster for repeat use, caching could be very helpful.  We could cache in our service what we get back from pinterest via some datastore or we could cache in our client.  Best practices here will be very dependent on your use case.  These kind of enhancements have been made over and over again and would only clutter the simple Pinterest interaction, so I will exclude them for now.</p>

<h2>Getting Pinterest Data</h2>

<p>Here's the final solution in all its glory.  This snippet only includes only the code inside the Express route.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
<span class='line-number'>29</span>
<span class='line-number'>30</span>
<span class='line-number'>31</span>
<span class='line-number'>32</span>
<span class='line-number'>33</span>
<span class='line-number'>34</span>
<span class='line-number'>35</span>
<span class='line-number'>36</span>
<span class='line-number'>37</span>
<span class='line-number'>38</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="c1">// request is a library for making http requests</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">request</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;request&#39;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="c1">// cheerio is a lib for screen scraping</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">cheerio</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;cheerio&#39;</span><span class="p">);</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="c1">// req and res are express vars for the request and response</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">exports</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">list</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">req</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">res</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="c1">// this is the actual request to the pinterest page I care about</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">request</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;http://pinterest.com/jaketrent/pins/&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">err</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">resp</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">){</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="nx">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="c1">// get ready for scraping</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">$</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">cheerio</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">load</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">body</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">pins</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="p">[];</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">$pin</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">$pins</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">$</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;.pin&#39;</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">// scraping only the 1st 10 pins;  you could get them all</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">for</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">lt</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="o">++</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">$pin</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">$pins</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">eq</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1">// Finding the bits on the page we care about based on class names</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">pins</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">push</span><span class="p">({</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">img</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">$pin</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;.PinImageImg&#39;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;src&#39;</span><span class="p">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">url</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s1">&#39;http://pinterest.com&#39;</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">$pin</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;.ImgLink&#39;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">attr</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;href&#39;</span><span class="p">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">desc</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">$pin</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">find</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;.description&#39;</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nx">text</span><span class="p">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="c1">// respond with the final json</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nx">res</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">send</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">pins</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="p">});</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">};</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>When I wrote it out for my own use, I was surprised at the brevity.  I love it.  Given, there's no handling of any errors or attempts to make this semi-robust.  This just gets us the data on a good day.</p>

<p>The final json that's exposed at our chosen Express endpoint looks like it this:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='javascript'><span class='line'><span class="p">[</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="nx">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="s2">&quot;img&quot;</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;http://myimg.jpg&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">&quot;url&quot;</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;http://pinterest.com/pin/mypin&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="s2">&quot;desc&quot;</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Sweetest pin ever&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="p">},</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="c1">// ...</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">]</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>It's ready for use by a json-ready client.  So stinkin easy.  We're connecting the web together, and it's awesome!  Now the world will know of the baked goods and flower arrangements that we love the most.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Npm Install Local Files]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/npm-install-local-files/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-14T08:23:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/npm-install-local-files</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes you'll want to use <a href="http://npmjs.org/">npm</a> to install a package that doesn't exist in the official npm registry for some reason.  Maybe you're developing the package yourself.  Maybe it's an internal use-only package. Maybe the package writer never published it.  Here are a few ways to install a local package with npm.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/xnDMm.jpg" alt="Node Package Manager" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Link the Local Node Package</h2>

<p>If you're developing a package locally, you're likely making lots of changes to the source.  You don't want to publish after each change in order to install this package as a dependency elsewhere.  Npm has provided the <a href="http://npmjs.org/doc/link.html">link</a> keyword.</p>

<p>This allows your put a global label on your package that tells your local npm cache about it:</p>

<p><code>bash
cd &lt;pkg_dir&gt;;
npm link;
</code></p>

<p>And then go to the local project that you're using the package in and point to the dependency by package name:</p>

<p><code>bash
cd &lt;project_dir&gt;;
npm link &lt;pkg_name&gt;;
</code></p>

<p>Now you have symlinked a directory called <code>&lt;pkg_name&gt;</code> in the project's node_modules directory.  Changes you make in your package will appear and be usable from within your project.</p>

<h2>Tarball the Local Node Package</h2>

<p>Npm can <a href="https://npmjs.org/doc/install.html">install</a> either a path or url to a local tarball.  To create a tarball that npm will like, you want to run npm <a href="https://npmjs.org/doc/pack.html">pack</a>:</p>

<p><code>bash
cd &lt;pkg_dir&gt;;
npm pack
</code>
This will create a tarball a la <code>&lt;pkg_name&gt;-&lt;pkg_ver&gt;.tgz</code>.  Now just store your new tarball somewhere like a local filesystem or server that is accessible when you run npm install on your dependant project.</p>

<p>You can ask for the tarball manually:</p>

<p><code>bash
npm install http://localServer/my-pkg-0.0.1.tgz
</code></p>

<p>Or put the reference in your package.json for later:</p>

<p>```js
{
  "dependencies": {</p>

<pre><code>"my-pkg": "http://localServer/my-pkg-0.0.1.tgz"
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>You probably have a node package that's only available locally for a reason.  To guarantee that it's not accidentally published to the world via the npm registry, add this beaut to your package.json:</p>

<p><code>js
{
   "private": true
}
</code></p>

<h2>Replicate the Npm Registry</h2>

<p>If you're going all out, like creating a corporate npm registry, you always have the option of <a href="https://npmjs.org/doc/registry.html#Can-I-run-my-own-private-registry">replicating</a> the Npm registry internally.  It's CouchDb, and '<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0120029/quotes?qt=qt0192627">replication</a>' is its Chinese neighbor's middle name.  You can publish your own packages there so they're still private to your and your organization.  And you also get local references to the public packages.</p>

<h2>The Glory of Npm</h2>

<p>Npm is great.  The ability to install published or local packages is an example of its flexibility and usefulness.  What are the other ways that you've found to make non-public packages installable -- for instance, that package that the writer just never bothered to publish to npm?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
