<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ide | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/ide/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-14T16:24:09-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IntelliJ 12 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/intellij-12-review/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/intellij-12-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've used IntelliJ since version 6.  Now we're version 12.  It's just gotten better.  Version 12 is definitely an incremental release.  There's nothing too whiz bang here that I care about, but the quality overall is increased.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/RM3Q1.jpg" alt="IntelliJ 12" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>IntelliJ 12 New Core Features</h2>

<p>The highlights of the <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/whatsnew/index.html">"What's New"</a> list include Java 8 support, Spring tools update, Play 2.0 support, and Android UI designer.  All positives, but not really things I care very deeply about and will probably never use.  There's a bit more on the list, but there's nothing that is a huge, "Now IntelliJ can do ______" item.</p>

<h2>IntelliJ 12 Quality of Life</h2>

<p>During my evaluation, however, I have been very pleased with the quality of life it has afforded me.  IntelliJ has always treated me very well in comparison to the competition.  IntelliJ 12 just makes that good experience a little bit sweeter.</p>

<h4>Darkula Theme</h4>

<p>This has to be inspired by the rise of <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/">Sublime Text</a>, which has a dark theme as its default.  More and more devs I know are using Sublime extensively.  Overall, I like the look of the Darkula theme.  It's a bit easier on the eyes.  The icons got a fun, retro overhaul.  In some cases, I've noticed things that my eyes have grown so accustomed to that they have ignored for some time.  It's also taken a bit to get used to it and start to expect things and see them faster.  I find it interesting that soooo much of this release has been focused on this UI theme.</p>

<h4>Popup Dialogs are Faster</h4>

<p>It seems that when a non-main window is told to appear that it does so a bit quicker now.  Intellisense seems a bit more snappy, and the "recent files" switcher doesn't lag as it seemed to in the past sometimes.  It's fun, and it lets me go faster.</p>

<h4>Better OSX Shortcuts</h4>

<p>When I switched to OSX from Linux, I was immediately disappointed by the lack of keyboard shortcuts in comparison to Linux.  The most egregious omission was the lack of alt-* combos to press buttons in the UI via the keyboard.  Alt-p to engage the 'push' button in the Git push dialog has been a long time coming.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/FYe1O.jpg" alt="P for Push" /></p>

<h4>Git Integration is better</h4>

<p>For performance and UI reasons, I would often just use Git on the command line instead of from within IntelliJ.  Now the Git integration is better than ever.  It seems waaaay fast.  I'm a little puzzled at <em>how</em> the git push could be so much faster in comparison to the previous version.</p>

<h4>Project Type Support</h4>

<p>Small thing, but I like the new "New Project" dialog.  It's simplified and easier to navigate.  It is fast and simple.  It doesn't take you through options that don't apply.  I'm in that dialog a lot, and I like the change.</p>

<h2>The Right Direction</h2>

<p>Really, there's not a ton new here.  It's such a solid tool to start.  It's where I spend most of my day though, so even incremental quality improvement is welcome.</p>

<p>Let's see, what's not there that I wish for?:</p>

<ul>
<li>Live debug the JavaScript running in Chrome (not just Firefox)</li>
<li>Run and debug Grunt and other Node-based cli apps</li>
</ul>


<p>Does IntelliJ already do those things?  Probably, and I just don't yet know how to bend it to my will.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hotdeploy in Intellij 8]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/hotdeploy-intellij-8/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-22T14:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/hotdeploy-intellij-8</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Development on JEE projects can be a real pain sometime.  1/2 of this (sometimes in literal minutes) is because of the need to spin up the server in order to run your code.  This server startup time can be a killer of one's development momentum.</p>

<p>True to its mantra, IntelliJ IDEA delivers some goodness is making this pain a little more pleasurable -- if that's possible.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Development on JEE projects can be a real pain sometime.  1/2 of this (sometimes in literal minutes) is because of the need to spin up the server in order to run your code.  This server startup time can be a killer of one's development momentum.  If one is trying to make a change to code and then follow through and check the resulting differences, it can be much like running downstairs in one's house to fetch something, forgetting what that something was upon arrival.</p>

<p>It seems that the solutions to this problem are varied.  For me, it has meant: - Coding webapps in interpreted languages
- Trying IDE-based hotdeploy schemes
- Trying 3rd-party plugins like JavaRebel.</p>

<p>I have had problems with all 3 solutions:
- These are fun, but not what my employer uses
- I haven't found an IDE yet that hotdeploys to my liking.  It's always extremely hard to tell if an IDE has really done its job and if what the browser is giving back to me is the new version. Eclipse has tried to give a visual indicator with its 'Published'/'Republish' verbage in its Servers view, but it seems that this indicator is often wrong.
- I haven't had hardly any luck with JavaRebel.  Pre-version 1.0, it seemed buggy.  Then, I had problems integrating it with my IDE's build/deploy process.  Since the version 1.0 release, I haven't tried it again, but I hear it's still buggy.</p>

<p>As imperfect as the solutions are, it seems to me that the current best solution to the Java webapp hotdeploy is still the IDE-based hotdeploy scheme.  As my favorite IDE is IntelliJ IDEA, here's a little 1-2-3 on how to get hotdeploy working in IntelliJ 8 (as of Milestone 1, Diana):</p>

<h3>Select two important options</h3>


<p>Go to Settings > Compiler, and set "Deploy web applications to server after compilation" to "Never"</p>

<p><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/qOoybG2F413C8IkbKljbug"><img src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/trent.jake/SNgOk1bJ1cI/AAAAAAAAENs/DTZhP4ZvYBk/s800/compileropt.png" /></a></p>

<p>Go to Settings > Debugger, and set "Reload classes after compilation" to "Always" and optionally check "Reload classes in background".</p>

<h3>Compile after a code change</h3>


<p>Now, every time you make a change to compiled code (e.g., .java files), make sure you re-compile.  The shortcut is Ctrl-Shift-F9.</p>

<p>And that's it!  Pleasurable development was meant to be fast and simple.</p>

<p>I'm a little unclear as to the essentialness, but as a general rule, I also set another option in the deployment settings for static file hotdeploy:</p>

<p>Go to Settings > Project Settings > your web module > Java EE Build Settings and check "Build on frame deactivation" and check "Build Web resources only"</p>

<p><a href="http://picasaweb.google.com/lh/photo/hsw-VeKzduwMGCANP4p5xg"><img src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/trent.jake/SNgSOwB4qyI/AAAAAAAAEOI/d07_gHC89nI/s400/projsettings.png" /></a></p>

<p>I haven't tested the utter-most limits of this hotdeploy.  I'm not really sure at their limitations, but I would guess that changes to method signatures or changes to descriptor files would require a server restart.  I am, however, unsure.  How about you?</p>

<p>Besides just the handy hotdeploy, one should also keep in mind that other things can help startup time: viva los smaller projects!  But, for anyone wanting to enjoy a behemoth, enjoy Napi.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
