<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-08T09:35:56-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Permit Array in Rails Strong Parameters]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/permit-array-rails-strong-parameters/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-22T11:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/permit-array-rails-strong-parameters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rails 4 introduced the pattern of strong parameters at the controller layer.  As a best practice, you will explicitly list the parameters that an endpoint should accept in payloads.  Arrays are specified just slightly different.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/XOUecnw.jpg" alt="Rails" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Strong Parameters</h2>

<p>You don't want those blackhats to update any field they want on your poor models.  Raise the shields -- strong parameters!  In ye olden days, <code>attr_accessible</code> could add some protection to your models.  Since Rails 4, it has been best practice to move this responsibility to the controller.  At that layer, you can make adjustments and allowances on a per-endpoint basis (eg, admin functionality has more power over a particular model than the layman user).</p>

<p>So, create a private function in your controller where you can filter your params for your model.  It might look like:</p>

<p>```ruby
private</p>

<p>def luchador_params
  params.require(:luchador).permit(:favorite_move, :weight)
end
```</p>

<p>You have two main methods to use:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>require</code> - ensures that the parameter is present (as in this root <code>luchador</code> key)</li>
<li><code>permit</code> - whitelist filters the parameters to the set specified</li>
</ul>


<h2>Arrays in <code>permit</code></h2>

<p>The most standard use case for <code>permit</code> is to pass it a collection of :symbols.  These keys must represent scalar values (string, number, that sort) only.  But what about arrays?  They're represented differently by an empty array:</p>

<p><code>ruby
params.require(:luchador).permit(:favorite_move, :weight, wins: [])
</code></p>

<p>But wait -- one more problem, and I don't like the answer here.  My client might send back a <code>nil</code> instead of an array (ie, when the luchador has no <code>wins</code>).  If this happens, cue ugly error:</p>

<p><code>text
Unpermitted parameter: wins
</code></p>

<p>To fix, default to empty array:</p>

<p><code>ruby
params[:luchador][:wins] ||= []
params.require(:luchador).permit(:favorite_move, :weight, wins: [])
</code></p>

<p>What have you done that looks better?  Please! :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debug Ruby and Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/debug-ruby-rails/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-14T07:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/debug-ruby-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Interactive debugging can sometimes be faster and more effective in helping you code than a <code>puts</code> statement.  It's easy to get interactive debugging in Ruby or on Rails with the help of a nice gem.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Z7WWtL0.jpg" alt="Ruby" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>No IDE Required</h2>

<p>There are Ruby IDEs that provide interactive debugging capabilities.  My favorite is <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/">RubyMine by Jetbrains</a>.  But if you don't have or don't want an IDE, there's still hope.</p>

<h2>Debugger Gem</h2>

<h4>Include the dependency</h4>

<p>My new buddy George showed me a sweet gem simply named <code>debugger</code>.  To use it, I first add the <code>debugger</code> dependency to my <code>Gemfile</code>:</p>

<p>```
source "https://rubygems.org"</p>

<p>gem 'debugger'
```</p>

<h4>Add a breakpoint</h4>

<p>Next, I need to add my "breakpoint" into my code that I'm going to run.  In this case, the breakpoint is defined by calling <code>debugger</code>.  On the same line, we'll also import the <code>debugger</code> library:</p>

<p>```ruby
  # ...
  def is_anagram?</p>

<pre><code>require 'debugger'; debugger
same_length? and different? and has_same_letters?
</code></pre>

<p>  end
```</p>

<h4>Run your code</h4>

<p>In this example, I'm going to break right after I call the <code>is_anagram?</code> method.  From the terminal, now I exercise the code.  In this case, I'll run my unit tests:</p>

<p><code>bash
ruby anagram_test.rb
</code></p>

<h4>Debug like a champ</h4>

<p>And when execution of the script gets to the <code>debugger</code> line, execution will pause and output in my terminal will look something like this:</p>

<p>```ruby
/Users/jake.trent/dev/exercism/ruby/anagram/anagram.rb:13
same_length? and different? and has_same_letters?</p>

<p>[8, 17] in /Users/jake.trent/dev/exercism/ruby/anagram/anagram.rb
   8      @letters2 = @word2.split('')
   9    end
   10
   11    def is_anagram?
   12      require 'debugger'; debugger
=> 13      same_length? and different? and has_same_letters?
   14    end
   15
   16    def has_same_letters?
   17      same_letters = true
(rdb:1)
```</p>

<p>A snippet of my code is shown, an arrow points at line 13, and there's a prompt at the bottom (labeled 'rdb') that you can type in.  <code>debugger</code> gives you a few special commands to type, such as:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>n</code> - next</li>
<li><code>s</code> - step over</li>
<li><code>c</code> - continue</li>
</ul>


<p>These commands should be familiar to almost all debuggers.  The other fabulous thing is that the prompt functions as a sort of <code>irb</code> session from the current context of your code.  So, I can type variable names to see their contents or call functions to see what they'd return.  So, in the case of this code, I could try:</p>

<p><code>bash
(rdb:1) has_same_letters?
true
(rdb:1) @letters2
["s", "t", "a", "n", "d"]
</code></p>

<p>Pretty cool and pretty powerful all for the price of including the library and including a breakpoint in your code.</p>

<p>Are there tools similar to this that you love to use for debugging?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Import Erb Into Karma]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/import-erb-into-karma/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T16:59:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/import-erb-into-karma</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rails asset pipeline allows you to use erb helpers in your CoffeeScript.  You'll still need to bring get these files into Karma runner.  It's really easy.  You just need to get to know your Karma config options.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/i5fJT6j.png" alt="erb files in Karma runner" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>erb in JavaScripts</h2>

<p>Why in the world would you want to use erb helpers inside your script files?  You might not.  I definitely think this should be a limited practice.  In some cases, it can be very helpful.  For instance, if you use Ruby/Rails (via <a href="https://github.com/rumblelabs/asset_sync"><code>asset_sync</code></a>) to upload your static assets to an external server, such as S3, you can help your scripts know where static assets live after upload.</p>

<p>So your script might use the <code>asset_path</code> helper and end up looking something like this:</p>

<p>```coffeescript app.coffee.erb
angular.module('app', []).config ($routeProvider) -></p>

<p>  $routeProvider</p>

<pre><code>.when '/admin',
  controller: 'AdminIndexCtrl'
  templateUrl: "&lt;%= asset_path('admin/index.html') %&gt;"
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<h2>Import erb Files into Karma</h2>

<p>Well, now you have an <code>app.coffee.erb</code> file.  You need to get it into <a href="http://karma-runner.github.io">Karma runner</a>.  Normally <code>*.coffee</code> files will be brought straight in and compiled automatically by the runner as needed.  In this case, however, the Karma defaults won't recognize the <code>.coffee.erb</code> file as a CoffeeScript file need compilation.</p>

<p>To tell Karma to process your erb file as a CoffeeScript file, add this to your config:</p>

<p>```coffeescript karma.conf.coffee
module.exports = (config) ->
  config.set</p>

<pre><code># ...
preprocessors:
  '**/*.coffee.erb': ['coffee']
  '**/*.coffee': ['coffee']
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>That's it.  That's the key to getting your Erb files processed into JavaScript and ready for Karma to use.</p>

<p>Now, what are your thoughts on putting your CoffeeScripts through the erb filter of the asset pipeline at all?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain West Ruby Conf 2013 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/mountain-west-ruby-conf-2013-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T15:23:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/mountain-west-ruby-conf-2013-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently attended the Mountain West Ruby Conference.  It was my first time going.  I was pleasantly surprised by the quality of the conference.  I would recommend it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ABNr5MC.jpg" alt="Mountain West Ruby Conf" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Peeps</h2>

<p>I'm new to the Ruby community.  I get to use it more in my current job than I ever have before.  Whenever entering a new community, it's good to find some friends.  I was pleased to notice that everyone I encountered at the conference was very friendly and welcoming.</p>

<p>About the coolest thing about the community is one of the slogans: MINSWAN, which means "Matz is nice, so we are nice."  How cool is that?  Matz is the Ruby creator.  Wait, who am I kidding.  You already know that.</p>

<p>I was very impressed with the blatant lack of trolling other communities.  This even with the live stream video cameras rolling (people can tend to do weird things when put on camera).</p>

<p>The conference attracted speakers and attendees from as far away as Australia.</p>

<h2>Speakers</h2>

<p>I didn't look too closely at the schedule previous to attending.  Once I got there, I was surprised at the caliber of those people and companies who were represented.  These were big names in the tech community, such as Matz, himself, Github, Heroku, and others.</p>

<p>The conference is single track, so that meant I got to see everyone speak.  I mostly like that but kind of hate that.  I believe it also meant fewer speaking slots, so everyone was pretty top notch.</p>

<p>I was impressed with the stage presence of most speakers.  A few were pretty droning, but in general everyone was very polished, had good slide decks, and shared engaging and useful content.</p>

<p>Devops was the stated subject matter of an entire day of the conference.  This was cool.  We can use that kind of focus on the subject.  But then it bled into the next days as well.  I want some pure code, pure Ruby'ness.  I got some of that, but not as much as I would like.  I paid my devops dues the first day.  I was ready to not hear any more of it on days 2 and 3.</p>

<h2>Venue</h2>

<p>It was in my back yard!  I loved the lack of a hotel requirement!  Apparently some visitors even camped in the wilderness, Nacho style.</p>

<p>The Salt Lake City Public Library is a great downtown location for a small conference.  In this case, with the conference being single track, the single largest room, the amphitheatre, was the only room required for all attendees.  It featured plenty of seating -- at the cost of no leg room.</p>

<p>The wifi also held up better than it has for similar gatherings in this space.  It was announced that "the city and Xmission are working feverishly" to maintain connectivity several times over the 3 days.  It still didn't stay up.  This is a common tech conf occurrence.</p>

<p>I was sorely disappointed with the lack of sugary confections meant to encourage the jollyness and attentiveness of the conference-goers.  At one point, it was necessary to slip out and find a good bakery downtown.  I was not disappointed.  I was happy to see at least the vendors' vinyl stickers come out on the last day.  We need more of that!</p>

<p>In all, it was a good use of my couple days.  It wasn't too pricey, but then, I wasn't paying.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setup Slim on Sinatra]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/setup-slim-on-sinatra/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-19T07:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/setup-slim-on-sinatra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.sinatrarb.com/">Sintra</a> is a light web server that's easy to start writing Ruby on.  Coming from Node/Express, I feel quite at home there.  Slim also feels like another JavaScript-world templating language, Jade, that I've had good experiences with.  <a href="http://slim-lang.com/">Slim</a> makes for quick templating and feels quite nice compared to ERB if you can handle the Haml style.  It's likewise quick and easy to get working on Sinatra.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Dsnu3jA.png" alt="Slim templates" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Quick Sinatra Setup</h2>

<h4>Require Sinatra</h4>

<p>Sinatra is super easy to setup.  Create a <code>Gemfile</code> with the dependencies as follows:</p>

<p>```ruby
source "http://rubygems.org"</p>

<p>gem "sinatra"
gem "thin"
```</p>

<p>Then create a default <code>web.rb</code> webserver with contents that look something like:</p>

<p>```ruby
require "sinatra"</p>

<p>get "/" do
  "Hello, world!"
end
```</p>

<p>Then if you run the command:</p>

<p><code>
$ ruby web.rb
</code></p>

<p>You should get a startup message like:</p>

<p>```
== Sinatra/1.3.4 has taken the stage on 4567 for development with backup from Thin</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><p>Thin web server (v1.5.0 codename Knife)
Maximum connections set to 1024
Listening on 0.0.0.0:4567, CTRL+C to stop
```</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Go to <code>localhost:4567</code> in your browser to try out your server.</p>

<h4>Require Slim</h4>

<p>Returning a string is all well and good, but let's include Slim to be able to create more sophisticated templates. Include your Slim dependency in your <code>Gemfile</code> with the line:</p>

<p><code>ruby
gem "slim"
</code></p>

<p>Then from the Terminal, run:</p>

<p><code>
$ bundle install
</code></p>

<h4>Setup your Views</h4>

<p>Then create a directory next to your <code>web.rb</code> file called <code>views</code>.  Inside <code>views</code>, you can create your templates.  You can create a layout template aptly named <code>layout.slim</code>.  By default, your templates will extend from this layout.  Most simply, these files might look like this:</p>

<p>layout.slim:</p>

<p>```haml
doctype html
html
  head</p>

<pre><code>title My Slim Templates App
</code></pre>

<p>  body</p>

<pre><code>= yield
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>And, index.slim:</p>

<p><code>haml
h1 Loving Slim
</code></p>

<h4>Serve a Slim File</h4>

<p>And now to adjust our <code>web.rb</code> file to serve the new <code>index.slim</code> file:</p>

<p>```ruby
require "sinatra"
require "slim"</p>

<p>get "/" do
  slim :index
end
```</p>

<p>Finally restart your server, and you should see your new template shown in all it's glory.  Pretty easy cheesy.</p>

<h2>Setup Slim on Rails</h2>

<p>Want something even easier?  Well, if you know <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a> already, this will be a cinch.  The hardest part of getting Slim running on Rails is Rails itself.  Slim integration is even easier than on Sinatra.  Simply add this line to your Gemfile:</p>

<p><code>
gem "slim-rails"
</code></p>

<p>And then in order to activate the Slim handler, merely add the <code>.slim</code> extension onto the end of any of your template file names.  Your file names probably end in <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/layouts_and_rendering.html"><code>.erb</code> by default</a>.  Change the ones that you want to convert to Slim templates to look like:</p>

<p><code>
index.html.slim
</code></p>

<p>Now the Rails are even slicker.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
