<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-21T09:12:33-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain West Ruby Conf 2013 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/mountain-west-ruby-conf-2013-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T15:23:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/mountain-west-ruby-conf-2013-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently attended the Mountain West Ruby Conference.  It was my first time going.  I was pleasantly surprised by the quality of the conference.  I would recommend it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ABNr5MC.jpg" alt="Mountain West Ruby Conf" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Peeps</h2>

<p>I'm new to the Ruby community.  I get to use it more in my current job than I ever have before.  Whenever entering a new community, it's good to find some friends.  I was pleased to notice that everyone I encountered at the conference was very friendly and welcoming.</p>

<p>About the coolest thing about the community is one of the slogans: MINSWAN, which means "Matz is nice, so we are nice."  How cool is that?  Matz is the Ruby creator.  Wait, who am I kidding.  You already know that.</p>

<p>I was very impressed with the blatant lack of trolling other communities.  This even with the live stream video cameras rolling (people can tend to do weird things when put on camera).</p>

<p>The conference attracted speakers and attendees from as far away as Australia.</p>

<h2>Speakers</h2>

<p>I didn't look too closely at the schedule previous to attending.  Once I got there, I was surprised at the caliber of those people and companies who were represented.  These were big names in the tech community, such as Matz, himself, Github, Heroku, and others.</p>

<p>The conference is single track, so that meant I got to see everyone speak.  I mostly like that but kind of hate that.  I believe it also meant fewer speaking slots, so everyone was pretty top notch.</p>

<p>I was impressed with the stage presence of most speakers.  A few were pretty droning, but in general everyone was very polished, had good slide decks, and shared engaging and useful content.</p>

<p>Devops was the stated subject matter of an entire day of the conference.  This was cool.  We can use that kind of focus on the subject.  But then it bled into the next days as well.  I want some pure code, pure Ruby'ness.  I got some of that, but not as much as I would like.  I paid my devops dues the first day.  I was ready to not hear any more of it on days 2 and 3.</p>

<h2>Venue</h2>

<p>It was in my back yard!  I loved the lack of a hotel requirement!  Apparently some visitors even camped in the wilderness, Nacho style.</p>

<p>The Salt Lake City Public Library is a great downtown location for a small conference.  In this case, with the conference being single track, the single largest room, the amphitheatre, was the only room required for all attendees.  It featured plenty of seating -- at the cost of no leg room.</p>

<p>The wifi also held up better than it has for similar gatherings in this space.  It was announced that "the city and Xmission are working feverishly" to maintain connectivity several times over the 3 days.  It still didn't stay up.  This is a common tech conf occurrence.</p>

<p>I was sorely disappointed with the lack of sugary confections meant to encourage the jollyness and attentiveness of the conference-goers.  At one point, it was necessary to slip out and find a good bakery downtown.  I was not disappointed.  I was happy to see at least the vendors' vinyl stickers come out on the last day.  We need more of that!</p>

<p>In all, it was a good use of my couple days.  It wasn't too pricey, but then, I wasn't paying.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setup Slim on Sinatra]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/setup-slim-on-sinatra/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-19T07:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/setup-slim-on-sinatra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.sinatrarb.com/">Sintra</a> is a light web server that's easy to start writing Ruby on.  Coming from Node/Express, I feel quite at home there.  Slim also feels like another JavaScript-world templating language, Jade, that I've had good experiences with.  <a href="http://slim-lang.com/">Slim</a> makes for quick templating and feels quite nice compared to ERB if you can handle the Haml style.  It's likewise quick and easy to get working on Sinatra.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/Dsnu3jA.png" alt="Slim templates" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Quick Sinatra Setup</h2>

<h4>Require Sinatra</h4>

<p>Sinatra is super easy to setup.  Create a <code>Gemfile</code> with the dependencies as follows:</p>

<p>```ruby
source "http://rubygems.org"</p>

<p>gem "sinatra"
gem "thin"
```</p>

<p>Then create a default <code>web.rb</code> webserver with contents that look something like:</p>

<p>```ruby
require "sinatra"</p>

<p>get "/" do
  "Hello, world!"
end
```</p>

<p>Then if you run the command:</p>

<p><code>
$ ruby web.rb
</code></p>

<p>You should get a startup message like:</p>

<p>```
== Sinatra/1.3.4 has taken the stage on 4567 for development with backup from Thin</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><p>Thin web server (v1.5.0 codename Knife)
Maximum connections set to 1024
Listening on 0.0.0.0:4567, CTRL+C to stop
```</p></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Go to <code>localhost:4567</code> in your browser to try out your server.</p>

<h4>Require Slim</h4>

<p>Returning a string is all well and good, but let's include Slim to be able to create more sophisticated templates. Include your Slim dependency in your <code>Gemfile</code> with the line:</p>

<p><code>ruby
gem "slim"
</code></p>

<p>Then from the Terminal, run:</p>

<p><code>
$ bundle install
</code></p>

<h4>Setup your Views</h4>

<p>Then create a directory next to your <code>web.rb</code> file called <code>views</code>.  Inside <code>views</code>, you can create your templates.  You can create a layout template aptly named <code>layout.slim</code>.  By default, your templates will extend from this layout.  Most simply, these files might look like this:</p>

<p>layout.slim:</p>

<p>```haml
doctype html
html
  head</p>

<pre><code>title My Slim Templates App
</code></pre>

<p>  body</p>

<pre><code>= yield
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>And, index.slim:</p>

<p><code>haml
h1 Loving Slim
</code></p>

<h4>Serve a Slim File</h4>

<p>And now to adjust our <code>web.rb</code> file to serve the new <code>index.slim</code> file:</p>

<p>```ruby
require "sinatra"
require "slim"</p>

<p>get "/" do
  slim :index
end
```</p>

<p>Finally restart your server, and you should see your new template shown in all it's glory.  Pretty easy cheesy.</p>

<h2>Setup Slim on Rails</h2>

<p>Want something even easier?  Well, if you know <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a> already, this will be a cinch.  The hardest part of getting Slim running on Rails is Rails itself.  Slim integration is even easier than on Sinatra.  Simply add this line to your Gemfile:</p>

<p><code>
gem "slim-rails"
</code></p>

<p>And then in order to activate the Slim handler, merely add the <code>.slim</code> extension onto the end of any of your template file names.  Your file names probably end in <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/layouts_and_rendering.html"><code>.erb</code> by default</a>.  Change the ones that you want to convert to Slim templates to look like:</p>

<p><code>
index.html.slim
</code></p>

<p>Now the Rails are even slicker.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jumpstart Lab Ruby Training Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/jumpstartlab-ruby-training-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-19T07:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/jumpstartlab-ruby-training-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://jumpstartlab.com/">Jumpstart Lab</a> offers a <a href="http://www.jumpstartlab.com/courses/">Ruby training</a>.  I recently attended.  I had a great experience and learned a lot in my first real introduction to Ruby and Ruby on Rails.  I would highly recommend the course.  Here are a few more details on my experience.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DniDljD.png" alt="Jumpstart Lab" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Format</h2>

<h4>Length</h4>

<p>Jumpstart sent a great instructor, <a href="https://twitter.com/franklinwebber">Franklin Webber</a>, to come lead us through the exercises.  The course was on site at our company.  It was 5 days in length.  Instruction went from 9am to 4pm daily, with a 1 hour break at lunch time.</p>

<h4>Breaks</h4>

<p>Exercises throughout the day were split up into 25 min time chunks with 5 min breaks following.  Some will recognize this usual time chunks for the <a href="http://www.pomodorotechnique.com/">Pomodoro technique</a>.  Frank, as the leader of the exercises, was more strict in his observance of the Pomodoro time slices than I'm used to seeing.  Many people I've worked with would work right through a short break, but we took breaks quite religiously.</p>

<h4>Content Split</h4>

<p>In our 5 day training, we spent about the first 3 days going over vanilla Ruby.  The next 2 days, we focused on the Ruby on Rails framework specifically.</p>

<h2>Approach</h2>

<h4>TDD</h4>

<p>Probably about the coolest aspect of this training was its relying on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">TDD</a> to get stuff done.  Often training courses, especially those that introduce brand new languages and concepts, leave testing as a tack-on feature, meantioned in parting near the end of the course.  Thankfully, Jumpstart did a great job integrating this best practice into most of its instruction.</p>

<p>We used <a href="https://www.relishapp.com/rspec">Rspec</a> as a test runner.  We used <a href="https://github.com/guard/guard">Guard</a> to help us go faster through our test iterations.  We discussed what to test, how to make our tests more readable, how to isolate tests using <a href="https://relishapp.com/rspec/rspec-mocks/docs">mocks</a>, and practiced doing lots of tests.</p>

<p>Only the Rails portion of the course was taught using error-driven development.  This actually worked quite well, as learning to use a framework requires learning how the pieces connect and trying not to test the framework.</p>

<h4>Instructor-Led</h4>

<p>Frank made the class successful.  He is super knowledgeable about the subject matter.  He is fun and funny.  He is great at introducing topics that built upon each other.  He is great at letting the students figure things out for themselves and jumping in at the right moment to help clear hurdles.  It was great to meet and work with Frank, and I hope to do so again.</p>

<h2>Bonuses</h2>

<h4>Hack Night</h4>

<p>We do a <a href="http://tannerhack.eventbrite.com/">hack night</a> every other week at work anyway.  Since Frank was here, he led the hack night.  We did a Codemash kata exercise where we created code to generate a <a href="https://github.com/jaketrent/minesweeper">Minesweeper</a> board.  We split into teams and pair-programmed our different solutions.  Everyone came up with unique solutions, we compared them, and then iterated.  I had so much fun with the exercise, I put a frontend on the game and made it <a href="http://minemopper.herokuapp.com">playable</a>.</p>

<h4>Tutorial Content</h4>

<p>Jumpstart printed materials for us in a booklet.  The <a href="http://tutorials.jumpstartlab.com">tutorials</a> are also available online.  Frank took a unique path through the content, and we talked through our specific approach.  As he worked, Frank also <a href="https://github.com/burtlo/training-021113">uploaded the code</a> from our instruction to Github.  I did the same for <a href="http://github.com/jaketrent/ruby-training">my code</a>.</p>

<h4>Recommendation</h4>

<p>I think that this training series was about the best I've attended.  I'm doing a lot more Ruby and Rails in my current job than I expected even a few weeks ago, so it was very timely and useful for me.  The content was good, but it was the instruction that made it top notch.  Thanks, Frank and Jumpstart, for the great experience!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Multiple Yields in an ERB Template]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/multiple-yields-in-erb-template/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-08T07:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/multiple-yields-in-erb-template</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you setup a new Rails project, you'll have a single layout file which has a single default <code>yield</code> block.  This will soon be inadequate, and you'll want another.  Here's how to setup multiple <code>yield</code> blocks per ERB template.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/YqUKEfw.png" alt="Multiple ERB yields" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Layout File</h2>

<p>By default, Rails will create a file at:</p>

<p><code>
app/views/layouts/application.html.erb
</code></p>

<p>In this file, there will be a default <code>yield</code> block similar to this:</p>

<p><code>ruby
&lt;%= yield %&gt;
</code></p>

<p>It has no name.  It's just the default place for templates that use this layout file to put their content.</p>

<p>We can create new <code>yield</code> blocks.  We'll have to give them a distinguishing name.  They look about the same.  If I wanted to create a new <code>yield</code> block where, for instance, alerts could be displayed if the child template had them, I could put this in my layout file:</p>

<p><code>ruby
&lt;%= yield(:alert) %&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Now I would just need something to go in it.</p>

<h2>Child Templates</h2>

<p>A child template that uses the <code>application.html.erb</code> layout file can just start blasting out markup that will go into the default <code>yield</code> block.  This will usually be the main content.  But in our example, there might be more focused content such as alerts that we want to display in a separate area.  Thus, our template could potentially look like this:</p>

<p>```erb</p>

<h1>My main content</h1>


<p>Bacon ipsum…<p>

<% content_for :alert do %>
  <div class="alert alert-success">
    You created multiple yield blocks!
  </div>
<% end %>
```

Throw down a `content_for` block, matching the name of the `yield` block in your layout file, and you're set.  Order does not matter.  Your specific `content_for` blocks can come before, after, or in the middle of your main content.  Easy as Ruby pie.

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rename Files in Rails Asset Pipeline]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/rename-files-in-asset-pipeline/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-06T07:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/rename-files-in-asset-pipeline</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rails provides a powerful mechanism for preparing your site's static assets for the web.  It's called the asset pipeline.  True to Rails, it has sensible defaults.  Also true to form, it's not immediately clear what's required to change from the defaults.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/HPJDXPB.jpg" alt="Asset Pipeline" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Multiple Compilers</h2>

<p>The asset pipeline has the ability to pass your static assets through multiple compilers.  Thus, they seem much less static than they might be.  The compilers used are determined by the file extension.  For instance, this file:</p>

<p><code>
myscripts.js.coffee.erb
</code></p>

<p>Will go through the Erb compiler first, then the Coffeescript compiler, then finally will output pure JavaScript.</p>

<p>Changing these files are no problem.  Want a new compiler?  Slap on a new file extension.  Don't need one?  Remove it.</p>

<h2>Manifest File</h2>

<p>Manifest files are full of Sprocket directives.  Sprockets will use these files to combine and minify your css and js.  A manifest will look something like this:</p>

<p><code>
//= require vendor/jquery
//= require vendor/angular.min
//= require vendor/angular-cookies
</code></p>

<p>These directives identify what files will eventually be combined, replacing the contents of your manifest file in the final output.</p>

<p>If you change the name of scripts or stylesheets, you need to ensure that your manifest file is changed to match.  Otherwise, asset precompilation will fail.</p>

<p>By default the manifest filenames are these:</p>

<p><code>
app/assets/javascripts/application.js
app/assets/stylesheets/application.css
</code></p>

<h2>Changing Manifest Filenames</h2>

<p>Changing the manifest default filenames will require some tweaking.</p>

<p>For instance, if I change application.js to be split into two separate manifest files, <code>scripts-foot.js</code> and <code>scripts-head.js</code>, the next time I run:</p>

<p><code>
rake assets:precompile
</code></p>

<p>It will succceed, and everything will look like it's just fine.  But when I go to run the app, it will give my an error like:</p>

<p>```
ActionView::Template::Error (scripts-head.js isn't precompiled):</p>

<p>2013-02-04T16:24:05+00:00 app[web.1]: app/views/layouts/application.html.erb:14:in `_app_views_layouts_application_html_erb__3761578772688930207_28706600'
```</p>

<p>When you switch from the default manifest files or when you reference a static asset like a js or css directly from your view, you'll need to mark it as explicitly requiring precompilation.</p>

<p>This is done in an environment file, such as <code>config/environments/production.rb</code>:</p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>Precompile additional assets (application.js, application.css, and all non-JS/CSS are already added)</h1>

<p>config.assets.precompile += %w( scripts-foot.js scripts-head.js )
```</p>

<p>It's that easy.  It's too bad you have to wait until the app runs to discover this is a problem.  But now you're ready.</p>

<p>Now if we could only customize the directory structure under <code>app/assets</code>.  I would much rather use the path <code>js/</code> instead of <code>javascripts/</code>.  Does anyone know how?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
