<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-01T09:17:18-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Run a Pow Server on a VM]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/run-pow-server-on-vm/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-31T16:14:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/run-pow-server-on-vm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's really pretty cool how easy <a href="http://pow.cx/">Pow</a> makes running a Rails server.  <a href="https://github.com/rodreegez/powder">Powder</a> makes it even easier.  Here's how to run your Rails server via Pow on a VM in order to test IE.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/XdExdtS.jpg" alt="Pow Server" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Install Pow</h2>

<p>Get your Ruby environment otherwise setup for Rails dev. Then install <a href="http://pow.cx/">Pow</a>.  It's a nice little utility created by the folks at 37 Signals.  They have a short little install script you can run, as <a href="http://pow.cx/">referenced on the Pow site</a>.  Or, you can use a utility created to make it <em>even easier</em> -- <a href="https://github.com/rodreegez/powder">powder</a>.</p>

<p>To install, you'll need <a href="http://rubygems.org">Rubygems</a> installed, and run:</p>

<p><code>
$ gem install powder
</code></p>

<p>Then link your project to Pow via the command:</p>

<p><code>
$ cd &lt;my_proj_dir&gt;
$ powder link
</code></p>

<p>Make sure Pow is running:</p>

<p><code>
$ powder up
</code></p>

<p>And access your Pow-powered site by going to your project's address in your browser:</p>

<p><code>
http://&lt;my_project_dir&gt;.dev
</code></p>

<p>There are other options in the <code>powder link</code> step.  For instance, if you want to access your site through an http address different than <code>&lt;my_proj_dir&gt;</code> you can specify that.</p>

<h2>Install your VM</h2>

<p>There are a few different VM options.  My favorite is <a href="http://virtualbox.org">VirtualBox</a>.  It does hurt a bit seeing the "Oracle" moniker on it, but I've found it to be as responsive as a VM can be and generally stable.</p>

<h2>Install Internet Explorer</h2>

<p>There really wasn't another reason that you wanted a Windows VM was there?</p>

<p>I've had good success with  the project <a href="https://github.com/xdissent/ievms">xdissent/ievms</a>.  To download the IE-ready images, the README invites us to run this script in our shell:</p>

<p><code>
curl -s https://raw.github.com/xdissent/ievms/master/ievms.sh | bash
</code></p>

<p>It will download multiple parts of several Windows/IE VM images into <code>~/.ievms</code> and install them so they're ready to roll with VirtualBox.  Run this way, images for Internet Explorer 6, 7, 8, and 9 are all downloaded.  If you wanted to just download IE 9, you could run:</p>

<p><code>
curl -s https://raw.github.com/xdissent/ievms/master/ievms.sh | IEVMS_VERSIONS="9" bash
</code></p>

<p>Either way, this download takes quite a while to complete, but the shell script that's running it takes pretty good care of you, restarting on the last incomplete download part.</p>

<h2>Access Pow via VirtualBox</h2>

<p>Accessing Pow in the VM isn't bad at all.  Pow makes use of <a href="http://xip.io">xip.io</a>, which provides a wildcard DNS entry used by Pow and thus your app.</p>

<p>For the <a href="http://pow.cx/manual.html#section_2.1.5">next step</a>, take note of your IP by running <code>ifconfig</code>.  Then from IE inside of VirtualBox, point your browser at:</p>

<p><code>
http://&lt;my_proj_dir&gt;.&lt;my_ip&gt;.xip.io
</code></p>

<p>And you should see your project running in the VM just as you do from your better, native OS.  Pow!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
