<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: superagent | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/superagent/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-02T13:29:20-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Authenticated Supertest Tests]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/authenticated-supertest-tests/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-14T07:07:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/authenticated-supertest-tests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you're trying to test your authenticated URLs via supertest, there are just a couple things you'll need to do that aren't spelled out in the docs.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/PFUGV.jpg" alt="Supertest" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Supertest</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/supertest">Supertest</a> is a library written by the prolific TJ Holowaychuk.  It is a companion to <a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/superagent">superagent</a>.  Superagent provides a clean API for issuing HTTP commands.  Supertest ties into superagent for allowing easy assertions on top of those HTTP requests.</p>

<h2>Authenticated Requests</h2>

<p>Lots of webapps have portions of their sites that require authenticated to access, so it makes sense that there's a great need to test requests against these portions.  Yet in supertest, there's not a totally-straightforward way to login for the sake of a test and do subsequent requests under that login.  At least there's no explicit API for it in the current release.  But there have been <a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/supertest/issues/26">many</a> <a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/supertest/issues/46">requests</a> for it.  Who knows if it will come.  Given that we know the mechanism for session continuity between requests, cookies, we can make it happen ourselves.</p>

<h2>Login for Supertest</h2>

<h4>Use Superagent</h4>

<p>Supertest has no cookiejar for holding cookies like the sessionid.  But, superagent does.  So, we're going to need to import it explicitly.  A login helper could look something like this:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
var superagent = require('superagent');
var agent = superagent.agent();
var theAccount = {
  "username": "nacho",
  "password": "iamtheluchadore"
};</p>

<p>exports.login = function (request, done) {
  request</p>

<pre><code>.post('/login')
.send(theAccount)
.end(function (err, res) {
  if (err) {
    throw err;
  }
  agent.saveCookies(res);
  done(agent);
});
</code></pre>

<p>};
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>A few points:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>theAccount</code> information could come from anywhere.  You could use the same pattern from this login process to setup a newly-registered user as well.</li>
<li>The <code>request</code> parameter to <code>login()</code> is the supertest request.</li>
<li>After we post to '/login' and a response returns in the <code>end()</code> function, we are saving the cookies from that response (a login response should return with a 'Set-cookies' header).  This superagent agent (with the login cookie) is what we send back to the caller of the login helper via <code>done()</code>.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Attach the Cookies to Supertest</h4>

<p>Now that we've made login request and saved the cookies, it's time to make our authenticated request(s).  Easy cheesy.  A simple test to see if the login worked might look like this:</p>

<p>{% codeblock lang:javascript %}
var request = require('supertest')(app);
var login = require('./login');</p>

<p>describe('MyApp', function () {</p>

<p>  var agent;</p>

<p>  before(function (done) {</p>

<pre><code>login.login(request, function (loginAgent) {
  agent = loginAgent;
  done();
});
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  it('should allow access to admin when logged in', function (done) {</p>

<pre><code>var req = request.get('/admin');
agent.attachCookies(req);
req.expect(200, done);
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>});
{% endcodeblock %}</p>

<p>More jabber about the code:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>app</code> is my Express app.  This is your webserver.</li>
<li>We're importing the login helper, and we've called it one time before all the tests in our <code>MyApp</code> spec via <code>before()</code>.  This call to <code>before()</code> is asynchronous, just like our test in this case, because we have to do a full login to setup our test.  When the <code>loginAgent</code> is returned, we save it for use in our actual tests.</li>
<li>The test gets the best of both worlds.  When doing <code>request.get()</code>, we're using the supertest request.  So, we can then do cool <code>expect()</code>s on it.  Right before the request goes out the door, we grab the superagent <code>agent</code> and attach its cookies to our new request.</li>
</ul>


<p>In the future, perhaps there will be a more expressive way to do this that's worked into the supertest API.  For now, this strategy is the best I've found.  It's based on the method I originally found in <a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/supertest/issues/46#issuecomment-11679706">visionmedia/supertest#46</a>.</p>

<p>Is there a better way that you've found to do this kind of authenticated test?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
