<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Review | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-04T07:42:34-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ng-Conf Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/ng-conf-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T07:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/ng-conf-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ng-Conf just happened last week in Salt Lake City, Utah.  It was awesome.  Oh blast, I blew the punch line.  Anyway, here's my take.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/4swtO6x.jpg" alt="ng-conf" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Format</h2>

<p>Two days.  Early 'til late.  One track.  20-40 min talks virtually back to back.  Lightning'y?  When we broke for lunch, I felt relieved.  My brain could go into some low-power mode.  Breaks between talks were mostly announced as anywhere from 30 seconds to 3 minutes, this whilst yammering off a short list of swag winners.  The format encouraged content, and there was a lot of it!</p>

<h2>Line Up</h2>

<p>The conference was easy to look forward to.  Looking at the speaker list, I was immediately impressed.  At one point during the event, Aaron Frost said that they hoped if the Angular team would come that they'd get more attendees.  Yes, that was a draw.  It was fun having them there.  Core.  Very core.  I believe that about each member of the team took the stage over the two days.</p>

<p>The speaker list in total was very impressive.  There was a good mix of local and remote talent who came together to cover a broad array of Angular and JavaScript-related topics.</p>

<h2>Talk Quality</h2>

<p>Talk for talk, just numbers-wise, it was definitely one of the most high quality conferences I've attended.  Of course, there were some less-than-stellar presentations.  But, on the whole, I was more than impressed by the subject mastery and teaching ability of the speakers.  Thank you to everyone who prepared.</p>

<p>There were also some definite highlights: Dave Smith on directives, Vojta Jina on DI, Brian Ford on zone.js, and Julie Ralph on Protractor.</p>

<p>And one of the best parts is that each of these talks was recorded on video for a livestream and <a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/ngconfvideos">on youtube for later viewing</a>.</p>

<h2>Venue</h2>

<p>The conference was held at the Little America hotel in Salt Lake City.  It was a beautiful location.  The combined main ballrooms that the talks were held in were awesome.  Plenty of marble.  The food was great.  There weren't tons of snacks, but that was probably good for my health.  The air quality in Salt Lake during the conference wasn't good.  In fact, oobleck!  But, I didn't get food poisoning -- plus!</p>

<h2>Smooth</h2>

<p>I heard it said by multiple people during the conference that it was the best first-time conference they had attended.  Indeed, everything went Domo smooth.  The content was the star.  It was fun.  It was energetic (minus some confusing lack of screaming for all the sweet swag -- probably had something to do with the sheer amount, like clapping for the 3rd curtain call).  The AV crew did a fantastic job.  Usually, it's annoying to sit in an audience as video or audio problems plague the start of a talk.  That simply did not happen here, and it was oh, so refreshing.</p>

<p>Oh yeah, and sweet jacket!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developing an Ember Edge Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/developing-an-ember-edge-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-23T11:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/developing-an-ember-edge-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The latest book on The List at <a href="http://emberwatch.com/books">emberwatch</a> is <a href="http://bleedingedgepress.com/our-books/developing-an-ember-edge/">Developing an Ember Edge</a>.  It's a great intro book to Ember.js.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/85v8PQP.png" alt="Developing an Ember Edge" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>The book is published by Bleeding Edge Press.  Pretty awesome name.  It is written by Jamie White, Matthew Beale, Christopher Sansone, Wesley Workman, and Bradley Priest, quite the host of authors.  It turns out to be a very timely read for me.  The code in the book even uses some of ember-data 1.0 beta 3.  As of this writing, that's almost the bleeding edge.</p>

<p>I would compare the book to the <a href="http://emberjs.com/guides/">Ember.js official guides</a>.  It's introductory.  It definitely favors a breadth approach.  For me, but a wee Ember babe, it brings to light some interesting details about the Ember internals or at least the approach of the framework.</p>

<h2>Format</h2>

<p>I read the book in digital form as a pdf.  I love the digitalness, but I wonder if it wouldn't have had a bit more editorial review if printed.  Perhaps this is what Bleeding Edge Press means.  The code in the snippets was all smashed to the left, destroying most indentation reading assistance.  The code bits were also a smaller font size than the prose which made the switch between the two slightly awkward to my over-taxed eyes.  By the end of the book, I wasn't surprised when I found a typo.  There were a lot but not too many.  For someone of lesser OCD, it probably would've largely gone unnoticed.  Of course, considering the engineer audience of the book, maybe that doesn't exist.</p>

<h2>The Zen of Ember</h2>

<p>The book content is really good.  I felt like it helped me piece together why things are organized in Ember as they are.  I learned more of what the pieces are by themselves and how they're meant to interact together.  The authors were also kind to point out where some of the rough edges were in terms of design (or potential misdesign by app authors) and api changes.</p>

<p>I liked the mostly-breadth approach to the writing.  The book was good for a newb and remained pretty short.  Perhaps that's because there's not too much there as a general subject without bloating this book into an API reference book. [whew]  The book struck a good balance of being technical, readable, and giving good insight into the practical use of the framework.</p>

<h2>Ember Trackr</h2>

<p>The first half of the book covers the concepts and layers of Ember, approaching mvc in general, objects, application, routes, handlebars, views, controllers, components, and models.  This takes 54 pages.  The other half(+) shows the development of a ticket tracking app.</p>

<p>The development process shown is thorough, even including the tool install, project file layout, and ui styling.  The TDD of the app in total was awesome.  It's really step by step.  Sometimes this was a little painful, but you definitely don't miss anything.  The screenshots of test runners in terminals and the app in browser windows could have been cropped for easier reading with less vertical blank space.  The testing walkthrough was really great.  They even worked through a few "unexpected" errors as one might actually encounter them.</p>

<p>The app dev portion could probably have been cut short.  About the time they start into the user management screens, we probably could have called it good.  But, they do introduce some good, new concepts in the app dev section of the book.  For instance, he covers a little on containers and <code>Ember.run</code> as it relates to testing.</p>

<p>I'm glad I read the book.  It was helpful to my slingshot into the Ember atmosphere.  Boom!  Go get it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exercism Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/exercism-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-19T07:29:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/exercism-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Exercism.io is a fantastic site and tool that provides a wealth of daily code exercises.  If you want to learn to be better in a language, it's a great resource to do exercises and receive feedback.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/2oAEqBZ.jpg" alt="Exercism" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Origin</h2>

<p><a href="http://exercism.io">Exercism.io</a> was introduced to me by Franklin Webber of gSchool and JumpStart Labs fame.  He and his colleagues use it as a part of their instruction, and it's a great, free tool available to the public.</p>

<h2>Languages</h2>

<p>There is a fun array of language-learning possibilities inside Exercism.  It currently includes a varying number of exercises across these languages:</p>

<ul>
<li>clojure</li>
<li>elixir</li>
<li>haskell</li>
<li>javascript</li>
<li>objective-c</li>
<li>python</li>
<li>ruby</li>
<li>scala</li>
</ul>


<p>I'm currently running through the Ruby exercises.</p>

<h2>Starting Point</h2>

<p>Based on what I've seen of the Ruby and JavaScript exercises, I don't think that Exercism's exercises are meant for an absolute beginner.  Some basic knowledge of the programming language is assumed and required.  You'll start a little deep if you know next to nothing.  These exercises are meant to expand your exposure to and understanding of language features.</p>

<h2>Installation</h2>

<p>Installation consists of a few things:</p>

<ol>
<li>Go to <a href="http://exercism.io">exercism.io</a> and register using your Github credentials.</li>
<li>While on the site, download the CLI.  It's a pre-built binary that you just need to put somewhere that is tied to your system PATH.  That way you can execute it from the terminal.</li>
<li>Setup your environment for the language you'll be learning.  Again, this information is on the site.  None of the environments are automatic in their setup, and you must follow the written steps to be ready to develop in your weapon, er language of choice.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Your First Exercise</h2>

<p>After installation, you're ready for your first exercise.  On the terminal, type:</p>

<p><code>bash
exercism fetch
</code></p>

<p>This will download fresh exercises at the head of each of your language paths.  At first, you'll start on exercise 0 of each of the language paths.  Now, choose a language.  I chose Ruby first.  The first exercise was called <code>bob</code>.  Bob is a lackadaisical teenager who responds with smart remarks to whatever somewhat says to him.  Typical.</p>

<p>Bob comes with a suite of failing tests.  All the tests are written, and it's up to use to write the code that actually makes Bob function and the tests pass.  This is literally TDD or test-driven development, and yay for us, someone has already written the tests!  In the case of Ruby, the tests are written in a MiniTest syntax.  To run them, I'm typing:</p>

<p><code>bash
ruby bob_test.rb
</code></p>

<p>This is where I think we might be able to have a bit of a better setup with the exercises.  It would be nice to have the tests automatically run on a file watch as opposed to having to run them each time manually.  For this, I personally setup <code>guard-minitest</code>.  I would recommend the same.  Of course, I can only think that Exercism doesn't do this by default in order to simplify the environment setup process.</p>

<h2>Nitpicking</h2>

<p>After you complete your first exercise in some form by getting all the tests to pass, you can submit it to the site for feedback.  For example:</p>

<p><code>bash
exercism submit ruby/bob/bob.rb
</code></p>

<p>The CLI will give you a link to your now-online code, and you can go there to see your submission.  Others who have completed the same exercise will also be able to see your solution.  And this is one of the coolest potentials of Exercism.  Others can give you feedback on your solution, called "nitpicks" by default.  This is a great learning opportunity.  We are ready to take feedback given from the perspective of others in their experience with the language.  We can also give feedback, training our eye to be more critical in our observation and future writing of code.  It feels like a great outcome and a great potential community.</p>

<p>I have given nitpicks.  Of course, that's easier to do.  But, I am sad to say that I have never received any.  It's hard to tell how active the community really is.  I see quite a few submissions, but there are definitely fewer nitpicks than submissions.  There's quite a bit untapped community learning potential here.  To help this, I wish the system allowed you to unlock the next exercise in your language path without closing opportunity for nitpicks on submitted exercises.</p>

<p>So, have you used Exercism.io before?  Do you know of similar sites?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Start Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/start-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T07:54:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/start-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting tends to be one of the biggest hurdles that we must jump in order to find out what awesome we really have inside of us and let it shine.  In the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1937077594/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1937077594&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=jaktre-20">Start by Jon Acuff</a>, he gives great motivation and tactical steps for starting to find our awesome.  It's a hilarious, inspiring, and practical guide.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ERlkwHb.jpg" alt="Start Book" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Stages of an Awesome Life</h2>

<p>All of us go through 5 stages of life on our journey to find our awesome:</p>

<ul>
<li>Learning</li>
<li>Editing</li>
<li>Mastering</li>
<li>Harvesting</li>
<li>Guiding</li>
</ul>


<p>These stages used to be tied to age or tenure.  People used to go through them steadily, sequentially, almost a decade at a time.  Getting to your awesome will surely require significant time and investment, but now and in the future the game has changed.</p>

<h2>The game has changed</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Retirement is dead.</strong>  The economy will recover.  The ideals of companies and individuals and governments won't.  Don't expect to pack it in and sit for 3+ decades.</li>
<li><strong>Hope is boss.</strong>  For those that see themselves as wanted to add to something meaningful, the opportunities are many and they are now.  You don't have to wait until you're 50 and have built a non-profit empire for you to add to something fulfilling.</li>
<li><strong>The Internet.</strong>  Opportunities are always open for anyone with access and a will to learn.  You can enter a field and expand your influence in that field incredibly quickly.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Be 22 Again</h2>

<p>You can literally be 22 at anything.  You can decide to enter a field, begin accelerated learning, determine your focus, lay on the hours of practice, find a plentiful harvest because of your new talent, and eventually help others along the path you have chosen.  Then you can do it all again.  These days some people are doing this out of necessity as an "encore career" in the place of a retirement that will not arrive.  We can all revert to 22 in a new field of study or activity in order to expand our exposure, increase or ability, or make our lives more happy and fulfilled.</p>

<p>There is a joy and a great feeling of accomplishment and purpose in the way that Jon outlines life.  What taste would life have if it were not based on learning and becoming better?  The values my parents taught me from the youngest age have been marinated in similar ideas.</p>

<p>When we're young, we literally feel like we can do anything.  And we do, to our own ability.  At some point, because of our own insecurity, we may tend to only keep going in the activities that others have told us we're good at or that we discover some aptitude in.  There's nothing inherently wrong in this.  In fact, we should take advantage of those things.  The feeling that we need to get rid of is fear of starting anything else.</p>

<p>As we grow older, we can become more prone to pigeon-holing ourselves and our successes.  We fear failure.  We want to build on the good that we've already done.  We don't want to fall from what we have built.  If we remember the pure enthusiasm and joy of learning that we felt as a child, we will open up more fulfilling doors in our lives.  We will continue to find more of what our own brand of awesome looks like.</p>

<h2>Style</h2>

<p>Jon knows how to write a good book.  This book, like <a href="/post/quitter-review/">Quitter</a>, was very encouraging.  Also like his previous books, I was laughing out loud as I read it.  People on the train sharing my commute surely had moments they wondered about me as I laughed at Jon's prose.  And I think my wife was surprised more than once by the unstoppable laughter that ensued after several especially funny bits. Jon's book reads quickly and happily.</p>

<h2>What's Next</h2>

<p>Jon gives the kind of encouragement that I need.  I don't feel greatly handicapped by fear.  In fact, I feel quite confident in learning and making new successes in my life.  But, Jon does help uncover some of the more subtle negative messages that I can give myself that tend to hamper my progress and lessen my enthusiasm, shooting holes in my own boat.  And then he gives practical steps for getting the momentum of learning going in my life and taking advantage of those things for which I'm the trail to mastery.</p>

<p>So, what's next?  There's only to start.  Let new adventures begin.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So Good They Can't Ignore You]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/so-good-they-cant-ignore-you/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-17T22:35:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/so-good-they-cant-ignore-you</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1455509124/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=1455509124&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=jaktre-20">So Good They Can't Ignore You</a>" is written by Cal Newport.  He rejects the idea of following your passion in order to find the work you love.  Instead, he suggests the accumulation of career capital.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/VWjzM2c.jpg" alt="So good" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>What follows are the main sections or rules of the book with a few of my takeaways each.  The man is obviously steeped in science.  The book reads like laws of physics.  Well, not quite that dry, but just as precise and well organized.  I love reading him say, "In which I argue..."  Sounds very professorish.</p>

<h2>The Passion Hypothesis</h2>

<p>Isn't it true that when someone is trying to determine a career path or job, we often ask questions like, "Well, what do you want to do?" And give advice like, "Do something you're passionate about."  The author gives a few individual profiles of people who followed this advice without key ingredients and were, in the end, disappointed by the result.  He also points out a whole class of lifestyle designers who, in their delusion, <a href="http://jaketrent.com/post/quitter-review/">quit their day job</a> to live on their yet-to-be-created passive Internet income and aren't able to make it.</p>

<h2>Career Capital</h2>

<p>(In which) Newport argues that "working right trumps finding the right work."  Essentially, you worry more about what you are producing and the value you're giving (craftsman mindset) instead of whether or not it fits some passion you're predisposed to.</p>

<p>Career capital is essentially the collection of rare and valuable skills that you possess that the market is willing to pay for.  Without this, you will likely not enjoy your work.  With this, your ability to define and magnify your work is much greater.</p>

<p>The title of the book comes from Steve Martin, who remarked in an interview that aspiring comics didn't like his advice.  They wanted quick fix answers like, "How do I get an audition?"  But he would always advise, "Be so good they can't ignore you."  And most likely, judging by your name recognition of Monseiur Martin, he has worked himself to that level.</p>

<h2>Autonomy</h2>

<p>It is autonomy, not passion, that is most likely to help you love your work.  The amount of control you have in a job is likely to influence your liking it.  The more control, the better.  But, it doesn't come immediately.  If you don't have the career capital, you can't purchase it.  And if you're offered it, while you know you probably don't have the capital, it's probably a mirage.  But if you're so good they can't ignore you, your ability to set terms and influence your environment is real.</p>

<h2>Importance of a Mission</h2>

<p>"So good they can't ignore you" hardly sounds like your average work.  Instead it's likely that you're attached to a catchy mission.  You have a vision that people want to share.  You do work that people like to talk about.  Your name is known by peers and leaders in your industry.  You have made it to the edge of your field.  You are pushing boundaries, and are creating new fields, often mixtures of those you have expertise within.</p>

<p>These stages of achievement that push your career and humanity forward are significant.  Little steps or bets need to be made strategically and intentionally in order to create a habit of advancing your knowledge and skill.  The sheer investment required to get to these levels is immense.</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Newport's book was worth the read.  In fact, I recommend it to anyone about to enter college, desiring to start in a new field, wanting to scratch an entrepreneurial itch, or thinking of changing jobs.</p>

<p>His advice is solid.  It's more grounded and nuanced than the "follow your passion", feel good propaganda.</p>

<p>The writing is a little dry.  It's a short book at just over 200 small pages.  Still, it took me a bit to get through.  I wasn't exactly glued to the pages.  But I do believe the advice is invaluable if it influences one to throw all their potential ability behind producing their best work and becoming their best worker.  It reads well, but sometimes feels like a textbook.  Perfect for all that intentional learning we all want to do, right?</p>

<p>Most importantly, it inspired me to be so good they can't ignore me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
