<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Review | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-13T07:28:35-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IntelliJ 12 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/intellij-12-review/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-12T15:33:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/intellij-12-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've used IntelliJ since version 6.  Now we're version 12.  It's just gotten better.  Version 12 is definitely an incremental release.  There's nothing too whiz bang here that I care about, but the quality overall is increased.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/RM3Q1.jpg" alt="IntelliJ 12" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>IntelliJ 12 New Core Features</h2>

<p>The highlights of the <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/idea/whatsnew/index.html">"What's New"</a> list include Java 8 support, Spring tools update, Play 2.0 support, and Android UI designer.  All positives, but not really things I care very deeply about and will probably never use.  There's a bit more on the list, but there's nothing that is a huge, "Now IntelliJ can do ______" item.</p>

<h2>IntelliJ 12 Quality of Life</h2>

<p>During my evaluation, however, I have been very pleased with the quality of life it has afforded me.  IntelliJ has always treated me very well in comparison to the competition.  IntelliJ 12 just makes that good experience a little bit sweeter.</p>

<h4>Darkula Theme</h4>

<p>This has to be inspired by the rise of <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/">Sublime Text</a>, which has a dark theme as its default.  More and more devs I know are using Sublime extensively.  Overall, I like the look of the Darkula theme.  It's a bit easier on the eyes.  The icons got a fun, retro overhaul.  In some cases, I've noticed things that my eyes have grown so accustomed to that they have ignored for some time.  It's also taken a bit to get used to it and start to expect things and see them faster.  I find it interesting that soooo much of this release has been focused on this UI theme.</p>

<h4>Popup Dialogs are Faster</h4>

<p>It seems that when a non-main window is told to appear that it does so a bit quicker now.  Intellisense seems a bit more snappy, and the "recent files" switcher doesn't lag as it seemed to in the past sometimes.  It's fun, and it lets me go faster.</p>

<h4>Better OSX Shortcuts</h4>

<p>When I switched to OSX from Linux, I was immediately disappointed by the lack of keyboard shortcuts in comparison to Linux.  The most egregious omission was the lack of alt-* combos to press buttons in the UI via the keyboard.  Alt-p to engage the 'push' button in the Git push dialog has been a long time coming.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/FYe1O.jpg" alt="P for Push" /></p>

<h4>Git Integration is better</h4>

<p>For performance and UI reasons, I would often just use Git on the command line instead of from within IntelliJ.  Now the Git integration is better than ever.  It seems waaaay fast.  I'm a little puzzled at <em>how</em> the git push could be so much faster in comparison to the previous version.</p>

<h4>Project Type Support</h4>

<p>Small thing, but I like the new "New Project" dialog.  It's simplified and easier to navigate.  It is fast and simple.  It doesn't take you through options that don't apply.  I'm in that dialog a lot, and I like the change.</p>

<h2>The Right Direction</h2>

<p>Really, there's not a ton new here.  It's such a solid tool to start.  It's where I spend most of my day though, so even incremental quality improvement is welcome.</p>

<p>Let's see, what's not there that I wish for?:</p>

<ul>
<li>Live debug the JavaScript running in Chrome (not just Firefox)</li>
<li>Run and debug Grunt and other Node-based cli apps</li>
</ul>


<p>Does IntelliJ already do those things?  Probably, and I just don't yet know how to bend it to my will.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Paper by FiftyThree]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/paper-by-fiftythree/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T16:58:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/paper-by-fiftythree</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever showed up in the App Store looking for an app in a particular category and been overwhelmed at the number of choices present?  This is certainly the case for the drawing and art app category.  But, there is at least one art app that stands out clearly from the others: <a href="http://www.fiftythree.com/paper">"Paper" by FiftyThree</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/M0kYA.jpg" alt="Paper brushes" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Best Brush</h2>

<p>The best feature of Paper is the one you get for free: the fountain pen.  It is easily the best brush I've used on any art app.  I've tried Sketchbook and Sketchbook Ink.  They are no where close.  It has the most beautiful tapered edges.  It responds best to speed and direction.  It comes the closest to a real fountain pen.</p>

<h2>Gestures</h2>

<p>The rewind/undo feature is invaluable when drawing.  It is immediately available by using two fingers.  You can activate it anywhere on screen.  This makes for very fast iterations on a drawing.  It's both intuitive and fun.</p>

<h2>Flair</h2>

<p>The app has a great style.  It's minimalistic and focused.  The notebook collection is fun.  The page flip is fun.  The UI is simple and powerful.  The focus remains on the drawing, where it should be.</p>

<h2>Sharing</h2>

<p>Sharing is straightforward and fast.  Exporting your drawings into your photo library is easy.  It's just as easy to share on the web.  Tweet with "#MadeWithPaper" and you'll show up on their <a href="http://madewithpaper.fiftythree.com/">blog</a>.</p>

<h2>Pricing</h2>

<p>I get the fountain pen brush for free, and I'm happy.  You pay $2 to get each of their 4 other brushes.  The next coolest is definitely the water color brush.  It totally makes sense to pay for these top-notch brushes.  Each brush takes considerable time and effort to develop.  Other apps -- I'm looking at your Sketchbook -- might include a pile of brushes at a lower price, but they are simply not as good.</p>

<h2>Wish List</h2>

<p>There are a few things that I think the app is lacking:</p>

<ol>
<li>The color palette is too simple.  I would love more options.  Apparently this is in the works.  There are many interesting <a href="http://support.fiftythree.com/fiftythree/topics/colour_palette">suggestions for expanding the palette</a> made on their forum.  <strong>Update:</strong> The latest update has a <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3002676/magical-tech-behind-paper-ipads-color-mixing-perfection">sweet color mixing tool</a>.</li>
<li>A zoom feature would be nice.  The difficult thing would be mapping it to an intuitive gesture, especially differentiating it from the super-awesome rewind gesture.  The resolution is high (2048x1536), but it sometimes doesn't feel very high given that detail work is hard without a zoom.</li>
<li>Being able to change background/paper options would be awesome.  At this point, all you start with is a plain, off-white background with no texture.  The app is called "Paper", afterall.  Wouldn't it be nice to have some more options here?</li>
</ol>


<p>The product features are well-thought and the FiftyThree team obviously has a design philosophy.  So, my pining for new features is patient.  I love what they have thus far.</p>

<h2>Magical</h2>

<p>Using Paper really has been one of the magical moments of using the iPad.  It gives a slick experience that gets me drawing fast.  There are masterful, well-honed tools that make my art look good.  The use of gestures makes great use of the direct input ability of the touch device.  I've enjoyed many hours using Paper, and I look forward to more products from FiftyThree.</p>

<p>What is your favorite feature of Paper?  Or of another art/drawing app?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SORT Conf 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/sort-conf-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-10T16:57:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/sort-conf-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The sky lightens with the rising sun.  Wheels are on the road.  Friends are in the car.  The leaves are changing on the towering Wasatch mountains.  Finally, we pull up to the University of Utah Institute building.  Stepping out of the car, the October air is fresh and clear, high in the Rockies.  It's a good day for a tech conference.  It's a good day for SORT.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/q1cr5.jpg" alt="Wasatch mountains" />
http://flic.kr/p/bDP2fF</p>

<!--more-->


<p>SORT is an annual tech conference put on by the LDS Church.  The IT shops of the Church are all represented, including ICS, Family Search, the BYUs, CES, and probably a couple more.  Attendance last year, I think, was about 1200.</p>

<h2>Something For Everyone</h2>

<p>A unique feature of the conference is that there are soooo many subjects covered.  It's really kind of a joke the number of tracks that are represented:</p>

<ol>
<li>EIM</li>
<li>Architecture</li>
<li>Design</li>
<li>Engineering</li>
<li>Partner Summit</li>
<li>Infrastructure</li>
<li>Leadership</li>
<li>PM</li>
<li>QA</li>
<li>Requirements</li>
<li>Security</li>
<li>Sharepoint/CRM</li>
<li>Solution Mgmt</li>
<li>Other (misc)</li>
</ol>


<p>Holy cow!  That's a little nuts.  It started out as an engineering-only conference in 2009.  Since then, it's blossomed.  I feel like it has been a double-edged sword:  The whole office is invited and should have something to soak up there, but it feels like the engineering track has been watered down a bit.</p>

<h2>Mostly Intro</h2>

<p>The topics are varied.  It's often the case that there's so much going on that you don't know what to pick for each hour.  That is awesome!  Out of the presentations offered in the engineering track, I would love to see more intermediate or advanced topics.  More deep dives would be fun to geek out about.  I think we touch that in some cases, but in general, I feel that the presentations could be categorized as cursory introductions to topics.</p>

<h2>Free-flowing Sugar</h2>

<p>I am never lacking for ATP at SORT.  The day starts with a great breakfast.  Lunch is also delicious.  This year, both were provided by Kneaders bakery.  Between every session, there are plentiful mounds of various snack foods and refreshing beverages.  And being a conference put on by the Church, the drinks are top notch, ready for the Church membership. :)</p>

<h2>Entry to Speaking</h2>

<p>I have presented at SORT for each of the last 4 years.  You already know the bar can't be that high.  If you submit a paper, you'll probably be accepted.  I was 2 for 3 this year. :)  Some might worry that this would lower the quality of the conference material and presentation.  Yes, it probably does.  But, just like any conference, if you are a little careful in your schedule selection, you'll find some fantastic speakers and super-compelling content.</p>

<h2>A Yearly Highlight</h2>

<p>In all, SORT is a fantastic experience.  I look forward to it next year.  It's fun to review what I've learned and presented on in the past (Django, then jQuery plugins, then TDD on MarkLogic, this year BackboneJs).</p>

<p>It's at a great, close location.  The company is fantastic.  The topics are varied and interesting.  The two days are time well-spent to me.  I feel tired (a sign of lots of fire hose drinking).  I'm inspired to learn a few new things:</p>

<ol>
<li>Do more CoffeeScript</li>
<li>Try SocketStream</li>
<li>Use Postgres' row_to_json</li>
<li>Try LawnChair and IndexDb</li>
<li>Do some user media capture</li>
</ol>


<p>Did any of you go this year?  What do you appreciate the most about SORT or your most recent conference?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review for Platform]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/book-review-for-platform/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-25T16:46:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/book-review-for-platform</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How do you inform people of your next big idea? How do you motivate others to continue listening to you once you have their attention? In the age of the Internet, there are countless competitors in almost every space. To differentiate yourself, you'll need to create something truly amazing. But that's not enough. Get that product or service into the public eye, and engage the masses to take a look and spread the good word. Michael Hyatt shares how to build the <em>platform</em> upon which this process will happen.</p>

<p><img src="http://c.michaelhyatt.com/banners/platform/728x901.png" alt="Just over that rise" />
http://michaelhyatt.com/platform</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Is this book for you?</h2>

<p>Michael Hyatt's book, "<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Platform-Get-Noticed-Noisy-World/dp/159555503X">Platform - Get Noticed in a Noisy World</a>" is an impressive book. As the books second subtitle says, it's "a step-by-step guide for anyone with something to say or sell". As it turns out, anyone with a product, service, or idea fits in this category.</p>

<h2>The Gist of Platform</h2>

<p>His strategy, and book, is broken into 5 sequential areas:</p>

<ol>
<li>Start with Wow</li>
<li>Prepare to Launch</li>
<li>Build Your Home Base</li>
<li>Expand Your Reach</li>
<li>Engage Your Tribe</li>
</ol>


<h2>The importance of a blog</h2>

<p>The doesn't get too much into product creation. My favorite chapter on that topic was chapter 2, "Bake in the Wow". It contained great "wow" checklist items that will be insightful for your own product creation.</p>

<p>Michael's strategy centers around a blog, or as he calls it, a "home base". This is the channel you control. You control the content, the format, the distribution, the readership, etc. He fills most of the book with this advice. This is where your product or service happens. This is where you direct everyone.</p>

<p>The advice is specific: titles, lengths of posts, frequency of writing, language, policies, and more is covered. He also gives ample treatment to the effective use of Twitter. Throughout, I was impressed with his sharing of specific tools or websites that are helpful.</p>

<h2>One small, perhaps fundamental beef</h2>

<p>To me, section 2, "Prepare to Launch", comes before section 1, "Start with Wow". Why? Because you really have to envision your product before you create it. What is the product you'll create? What is the exact problem you are trying to solve? Who is your target market? How will you distribute your service?</p>

<p>As Michael says in chapter 11 on creating an elevator pitch: You must first achieve clarity yourself before you can spread the message to others. Would this not come before potentially time/cost-intensive creation of your product? Both sections are fantastic, by the way.</p>

<h2>Blog-like Style</h2>

<p>Mike covers a lot of ground in this book. The information is immediately relevant to anyone (everyone) who wants (needs) an Internet presence. The read is quick and easy with short chapters that get right to the point (essentially a blog post per chapter). The core information close to the surface with little cruft. The voice is conversational and compelling as Mike tells his own story of how he has developed a following online.</p>

<p>It's no wonder that his blog has garnered thousands of followers -- the book was a good read with great content for creating a strong online presence. Or was it?  It was enough to help motivate me to start this blog.  Did you find it helpful/original?</p>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
