<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: debugging | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/debugging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-26T09:24:59-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Debugging Remote Tomcat from IntelliJ with Style]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/debugging-remote-tomcat-intellij/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-13T10:54:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/debugging-remote-tomcat-intellij</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the worst things to debug can be something that works just fine in your local development environment but does not work in a deployed environment.  If you deploy to Tomcat, you can debug it remotely.  If you use IntelliJ IDEA, you can do it with style.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>IntelliJ makes it easy.  First, you want to click the runnable configurations dropdown and select "Edit Configurations":</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_mA-9kCcx0bs/TaXdzFFhpxI/AAAAAAAAABM/6FoV9E3FpII/s800/ConfigDropdown.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>Once in the "Edit Configurations" dialog, click the "+" Plus icon to create a new configuration.  Select "Remote":</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/_mA-9kCcx0bs/TaXdzLv6GAI/AAAAAAAAABQ/3giI8x9pZc0/s640/SelectRemote.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>This dialog is the last, and you will need to configure your connection:</p>

<ul>
<li>Transport: Socket</li>
<li>Debugger: Attach</li>
<li>Host: Either IP or hostname of remote server</li>
<li>Port: Must match debug port opened on remote Tomcat (address arg below)</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_mA-9kCcx0bs/TaXdzPI1ovI/AAAAAAAAABU/EU-fflxWQ1g/s800/RemoteDebug.png" alt="image" /></p>

<p>As is explained to you on the window, you need to be able to add JVM arguments to the remote JVM.  By now, let us hope that we're all using a JDK more recent than JDK 1.3. :)  In that case, you'll need:</p>

<p><code>java
-Xdebug -Xrunjdwp:transport=dt_socket,server=y,suspend=n,address=7007
</code></p>

<p>To get those args on the server might require different mechanisms by default.  My environment's deploy is automated to put the args on the JAVA_OPTS variable in:</p>

<p><code>bash
$CATALINA_HOME/conf/Catalina/localhost/tcat-env.conf
</code></p>

<p>But if your deployment doesn't apply JVM properties for your app, you can put them in:</p>

<p><code>bash
$CATALINA_HOME/bin/setenv.sh
</code></p>

<p>Like so:</p>

<p><code>bash
export JAVA_OPTS="-Xdebug -Xrunjdwp:transport=dt_socket,server=y,suspend=n,address=7007"
</code></p>

<p>Finally, restart the remote server, and your debugging port will be open.  Start your remote connection in IntelliJ and set a break point.  Exercise your deployed app so your code will be executed, and let the good times roll!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
