<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: handlebars | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/handlebars/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-10T18:41:09-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ember Parent Templates]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/ember-parent-templates/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T07:02:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/ember-parent-templates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://emberjs.com">Ember</a>'s convention of template hierarchy is very specific.  Learn it once, and you'll know it every time.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/x5HT4FN.jpg" alt="Ember and Handlebars" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Note:</strong> Code examples use <a href="http://emblemjs.com/">Emblem</a> templates and <a href="http://coffeescript.org">CoffeeScript</a>.  Vanilla Handlebars and JavaScript would work just as well.</p>

<h2>Outlets</h2>

<p>Ember templates make use of a special helper called <code>outlet</code>.  You can have one main, unnamed outlet or many named outlets.  The main thing to remember is that a child template will always render inside its parent's outlet -- so always put outlets in templates that have children.</p>

<h2>Application Template</h2>

<p>There is a top-most template that all of your templates will render inside of.  This is called the application template.  It is specified in one of two ways.  If you are including your templates as script tags, simply create a script tag that doesn't have a <code>data-template-name</code> or <code>id</code> attribute, a la:</p>

<p>```html</p>

<script type="x-emblem">
  h1 My Application
  == outlet
</script>


<p>```</p>

<p>If you are <a href="/post/precompile-ember-templates">precompiling your Ember templates</a>, which you should, you have a directory for templates.  You will put your file, called <code>application.emblem</code> in the root of that directory.  The contents of <code>templates/application.emblem</code> would be the same:</p>

<p><code>jade
h1 My Application
== outlet
</code></p>

<h2>Route Templates</h2>

<p>If you have a top-level route, it will have a top-level template.  Your route's template will have only the application template as its parent.  So, your about route:</p>

<p><code>coffeescript
App.Router.map -&gt;
  @route 'about'
</code></p>

<p>Will have an about template at <code>templates/about.emblem</code> and you could define a route as <code>AboutRoute</code>.  It will render inside of <code>application.emblem</code>'s outlet.</p>

<h2>Resource Templates</h2>

<p>Resources are interesting because you can nest other routes inside them.  Nesting routes will also result in nesting templates.  If I defined a <code>league</code> resource with a nested route for creating new leagues, it might look something like this:</p>

<p>```coffeescript
App.Router.map ->
  @resouce 'league', -></p>

<pre><code>@route 'new'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>There are two leaf routes (and thus templates) that are created here:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>LeagueIndexRoute</code>, which uses <code>templates/league/index.emblem</code></li>
<li><code>LeagueNewRoute</code>, which uses <code>templates/league/new.emblem</code></li>
</ul>


<p>Note that you create a <code>league</code> directory inside your <code>templates</code> directory for nesting these templates.  Precompiled templates will be created at:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Ember.TEMPLATES["league/index"]</code></li>
<li><code>Ember.TEMPLATES["league/new"]</code></li>
</ul>


<p>If you wanted to use the <code>linkTo</code> helper in a template to link to these routes, you would use this syntax:</p>

<p><code>jade
linkTo 'league.index' | List Leagues
linkTo 'league.new' | New League
</code></p>

<p>And now as far as templates, there is <em>one more</em> that we're missing.  There is a root league template that these two league leaf templates render inside of.  It should live at <code>templates/league.emblem</code>.  This template would be useful for showing UI elements that are common to all league resource things.  In the case where there is no such need, this template will probably only contain a single outlet:</p>

<p><code>jade
== outlet
</code></p>

<p>So the final template hierarchy for <code>league.new</code>, for example, is <code>application.emblem &gt; league.emblem &gt; league/new.emblem</code>.</p>

<p>There is a bit of a chatter on the Githubs about whether the root resource template is good form or not.  As in, why would you create a file that contains nothing but an empty outlet?  Couldn't the framework infer that if it was missing?</p>

<h2>Children Need All Parents</h2>

<p>Create all parents in your template chain, from the application template to the leaves.  The worst thing that can happen if you don't is that nothing will render at all, and no error messages will be displayed (pretty bad and unhelpful).</p>

<p>Most of the time, Ember will try to be helpful and give you a console warning:</p>

<blockquote><p>WARNING: The immediate parent route ('a') did not render into the main outlet and the default 'into' option ('p') may not be expected</p></blockquote>

<p>In other words: You're trying to render a child template that either doesn't have a parent template it needs or the parent template does not specify a main outlet.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Precompile Ember Templates]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/precompile-ember-templates/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-21T07:54:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/precompile-ember-templates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://emberjs.com">Ember</a> makes use of the wonderful <a href="http://handlebarsjs.com">Handlebars</a> templates.  These templates, in order to be performant, must be precompiled.  Based on the Ember docs, it's not abundantly clear how this is to happen.  Here's a solution that works well.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/x5HT4FN.jpg" alt="Ember and Handlebars" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Ember Docs for Precompilation</h2>

<p>Every official Ember doc will put templates in a <code>script</code> tag with the <code>type="text/x-handlebars"</code>.  But this is never how you'd write any serious (-ly awesome) app in production.  <a href="http://emberjs.com/guides/templates/handlebars-basics/">The docs</a> say:</p>

<blockquote><p>"If you are using build tools to manage your application's assets, most will know how to precompile Handlebars templates and make them available to Ember.js."</p></blockquote>

<p>Which tools?  Why would I want to precompile?  How <em>are</em> they made available to Ember?  Read, Ember journeyman, read on...</p>

<h2>Grunt</h2>

<p>We'd love for this precompilation to happen previous to the running of your app.  Again, this is in hopes of increased performance.  <a href="http://gruntjs.com">Grunt</a> is a great little Nodejs-based tool for build-level tasks.</p>

<h2>Emblem</h2>

<p>Grunt comes with a variety of plugins.  We're going to use one called <a href="https://github.com/wordofchristian/grunt-emblem/">grunt-emblem</a>.  <a href="http://emblemjs.com/">Emblem</a> is a fantastic templating syntax layered on top of Handlebars (still a dependency).  Its syntax looks very similar to Haml or Ruby Slim or Jade.  It may well be the most flexible of all of them, and it simplifies some Ember helper syntax very nicely.</p>

<h2>Versions Matching</h2>

<p>As I've said before, <a href="/post/match-ember-handlebars-version/">matching Ember dependency version can be a pain</a>.  With precompilation, you have one more dependency to match.  Now not only do you care about the version of Handlebars that Ember uses at runtime, but you care about the version of Handlebars that is used to precompile your templates.  If the precompile Handlebars version doesn't match the runtime Handlebars version, your app will die at runtime.  <code>grunt-emblem</code> helps immensely with this.</p>

<h2>grunt-emblem</h2>

<p>I haven't found another Handlebars precompile plugin that helps as much as <code>grunt-emblem</code>.  It solves the precompile version problem by letting you utilize the actual runtime Handlebars as the precompile Handlebars script.</p>

<p>It is also nice in that it puts the precompiled templates into the collection that Ember expects to find templates in, namely <code>Ember.TEMPLATES</code>.  As you can find on the <a href="https://github.com/wordofchristian/grunt-emblem/"><code>grunt-emblem</code> Github page</a>, your grunt config will look something like the following:</p>

<p>```coffeescript
matchdep = require 'matchdep'</p>

<p>module.exports = (grunt) ->
  grunt.initConfig</p>

<pre><code>watch:
  ember_templates:
    files: ['app/views/templates/**/*.emblem']
    tasks: ['emblem', 'livereload']

emblem:
  compile:
    files:
      "app/static/templates/ember_templates.js": ["app/views/templates/**/*.emblem"]
    options:
      root: "app/views/templates/"
      dependencies:
        jquery: "app/static/js/components/jquery/jquery.js"
        ember: "app/static/js/components/ember/ember.js"
        emblem: "app/static/js/components/emblem/dist/emblem.js"
        handlebars: "app/static/js/components/handlebars/handlebars.js"
</code></pre>

<p>  matchdep.filterDev('grunt-*').forEach grunt.loadNpmTasks</p>

<p>  grunt.renameTask 'regarde', 'watch'</p>

<p>  grunt.registerTask 'dev', [ 'livereload-start', 'watch' ]</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>This particular config has a couple other niceties.  Let me enumerate the awesome:</p>

<ul>
<li>Line 6 - Not only can we precompile the templates, but we'll precompile on the fly, whenever <code>.emblem</code> files are change in the specified directories.</li>
<li>Line 8 and 14 - We're precompiling <code>.emblem</code> templates, but this plugin can do regular Handlebars syntax as well</li>
<li>Line 16 - <code>root</code> is the substring that will be stripped out of your template name.  For instance, you don't want your template to be called <code>app/views/templates/home</code>.  Your home route in Ember will want your template called <code>home</code>.  <code>root</code> to the rescue -- bam!</li>
<li>Line 17 - These <code>dependencies</code> are the libraries that you use at runtime and that Handlebars needs at compile time.  As I said, this plugin simply rocks because of the ability to specify your own Handlebars script.</li>
<li>Line 23 - Remember how you used to have a whole list of npm tasks registered.  This little beaut will load all <code>grunt-*</code> dependencies.</li>
<li>Line 25 - <code>regarde</code> is a cool name, but I understand what <code>watch</code> means a bit better. Rename it.</li>
</ul>


<p>This setup requires the following dependencies:</p>

<p><code>
npm install matchdep grunt grunt-regarde grunt-contrib-livereload grunt-emblem --save-dev
</code></p>

<p>So now, seriously, go write some Emblem templates.  So fun, so precompiled.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Match Ember and Handlebars Versions]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/match-ember-handlebars-version/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-21T07:38:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/match-ember-handlebars-version</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://emberjs.com">Ember</a> is very specific about what version of <a href="http://handlebarsjs.com">Handlebars</a> it requires.  This is probably good, but it's also a pain to work with as different versions of the two libraries are released independently.  There are a few good tools to help us out.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/x5HT4FN.jpg" alt="Ember and Handlebars" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Released Independently</h2>

<p>In a prime example, recently there was a new version of Handlebars released: <code>1.0.0-rc.4</code>.  Ember happens to be on version <code>1.0.0-rc.3</code>.  That version has a hard dependency on Handlebars <code>1.0.0-rc.3</code>.  In other words, the latest Ember code relies on an older version of Handlebars.</p>

<h2>Bower</h2>

<p>If you include these 3rd party libraries in your source code under a <code>lib</code> directory or something of that nature, you <em>always</em> have plenty of work to do.  Naturally, you just copy in the exact versions of the scripts that are needed.</p>

<p>Hopefully you're trying to make use of a mostly awesome tool, <a href="http://bower.io">Bower</a>.  It helps you manage these 3rd party libraries in a way similar to npm.  You provide a descriptor of your project's dependencies, <code>component.json</code>.  And you install things similarly via the <code>bower</code> cli.</p>

<h2>Specify a Bower Version</h2>

<p>If I run:</p>

<p><code>
bower install handlebars --save
</code></p>

<p>It saves a dependency in my <code>components.json</code> for Handlebars for the latest version it could find.  This won't do for us.  We need to specify the versions.</p>

<p>Our strategy will be: take the latest version of Ember and then specifically match the Handlbars version.  Finally, we should type:</p>

<p><code>
bower install ember --save
bower install handlebars#1.0.0-rc.3
</code></p>

<p>As of this writing, that is the version of handlebars that is required.  Bower will recognize any semver git tag name or branch name after the hash <code>#</code> sign.</p>

<p>I like our version strategy for a project that is under active development in that it keeps us on the latest Ember.  But, if you're on a project that's been built to an Ember version and not deployed for a long time, you may want to make a very specific dependency out of Ember as well, so the two are guaranteed in sync for future deploys.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Every nth Item in Handlebars Loop]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/every-nth-item-in-handlebars-loop/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-03T16:55:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/every-nth-item-in-handlebars-loop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever wanted to do something special every nth time through a Handlebars loop?  The built-in <code></code> will loop through your items just fine.  It lacks a few features.  For one, you don't have access to the loop index, though you can <a href="http://rockycode.com/blog/handlebars-loop-index/">find it</a>.  Without the index and simple comparisons like modulus, length of the array, and equals, you'll be creating your own Handlebars helpers.  Here's an example of one.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.teamtreehouse.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/handlebars.png" alt="Handlebars js" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Extend the context</h2>

<p>Inside a block helper in Handlebars, when you call <code>options.fn</code>, you pass the context to the first block.  We can extend what attributes are available in that context.  The <code>everyNth</code> helper below extends this context with variables that are useful for doing "every nth" operations:</p>

<ol>
<li>isModZero</li>
<li>isModZeroNotFirst</li>
<li>isLast</li>
</ol>


<p>The code in full looks like this:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='js'><span class='line'><span class="nx">Handlebars</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">registerHelper</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s1">&#39;everyNth&#39;</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">context</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">every</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">options</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">fn</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">options</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">fn</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">inverse</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">options</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">inverse</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">ret</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="s2">&quot;&quot;</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">if</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">context</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">amp</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">context</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="nx">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="k">for</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">i</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">j</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nx">context</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">i</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">lt</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="nx">j</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">i</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">modZero</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">%</span> <span class="nx">every</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nx">ret</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">ret</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">fn</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">_</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">extend</span><span class="p">({},</span> <span class="nx">context</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">],</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">isModZero</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">modZero</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">isModZeroNotFirst</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">modZero</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">amp</span><span class="p">;</span><span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">amp</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span><span class="nx">gt</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nx">isLast</span><span class="o">:</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="nx">context</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="p">}));</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="p">}</span> <span class="k">else</span> <span class="p">{</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">pre</span><span class="o">&gt;&lt;</span><span class="nx">code</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="nx">ret</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">inverse</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">this</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="err">/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nx">p</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>  <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">ret</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">});</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Note: This implementation uses <a href="http://underscorejs.org/#extend">underscore <code>_.extend()</code></a>.</p>

<h2>Scenario: Print rows</h2>

<p>Here's a scenario where this is useful:  In twitter bootstrap, each "span" div is inside of a "row-fluid" div (if using bootstrap responsive.css).  So, if I want three things, let's say videos, per row printed in the markup, you can't just use <code></code> because all it does is iterate through the videos.  You could print the "span4"s but you wouldn't know when to print the "row-fluid".  Hence, we need our helper.</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'>{{#everyNth myArray theNumberN}}
</span><span class='line'>{{/everyNth}}
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Our new helper <code>everyNth</code> allows us to write code like this:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
<span class='line-number'>28</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='html'><span class='line'>{{#everyNth vids 3}}
</span><span class='line'>  {{#if isModZeroNotFirst}}<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;</span><span class="ni">&amp;lt;</span>/div<span class="ni">&amp;gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>  {{/if}}
</span><span class='line'>  {{#if isModZero}}<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;</span><span class="ni">&amp;lt;</span>div class=&quot;row-fluid&quot;<span class="ni">&amp;gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>  {{/if}}
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">&quot;span4&quot;</span><span class="nt">&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;</span><span class="ni">&amp;lt;</span>div class=&quot;thumb&quot;<span class="ni">&amp;gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="ni">&amp;lt;</span>a href=&quot;{{ linkUrl }}&quot;<span class="ni">&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</span>img src=&quot;{{ image }}&quot; /<span class="ni">&amp;gt;&amp;lt;</span>/a<span class="ni">&amp;gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="ni">&amp;lt;</span>/div<span class="ni">&amp;gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>  <span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  {{#if isLast}}<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;</span><span class="ni">&amp;lt;</span>/div<span class="ni">&amp;gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>  {{/if}}
</span><span class='line'>{{/everyNth}}
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>To clarify the need and usage of these new variables:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>isModZero</strong> - in this example, every 3 videos should be on a row.  When mod 3 is 0, create a row.</li>
<li><strong>isModZeroNotFirst</strong> - when I create a row (mod 3 is 0), I also need to end the row, except before the first row.</li>
<li><strong>isLast</strong> - if the length of the video array is not divisible by 3, the last row needs to close anyway.</li>
</ol>


<p>The helper is simple, essentially just a copy of <code>#each</code> with a few new variables in context.  That's the beauty of Handlebars helpers.  With this little baby you can determine where you are in your iterations through your array.</p>

<p>What are some of the things you use Handlebars helpers for?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
