<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conf | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/conf/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-29T22:40:28-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain West JavaScript Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/mtnwest-javascript-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T11:45:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/mtnwest-javascript-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>MountainWest JavaScript was a great conference last week.  It was a jubilee. Well, if you can have a jubilee in the first year of a conference.   Here's my take.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/VGtnQzX.png" alt="MtnWest JavaScript" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Format</h2>

<p><a href="http://mtnwestjs.org/">MountainWest JavaScript</a> started this year as a part of the larger Mountain West conference set, including <a href="http://mtnwestdevops.org/">devops</a> and <a href="http://mtnwestrubyconf.org/">Ruby</a> as well.  It was two full days.  There is a single track -- everyone (that stays) hears everything.  Love both these features.  Splitting the disciplines into separate conferences is genius.</p>

<h2>Speakers</h2>

<p>The speaker lineup was exceptional.  There were many great minds assembled, fun experience shared, and great companies represented.  Following <a href="/post/ng-conf-review/">ng-conf</a> earlier this year, I was again pleasantly surprised at the amount of great content.  I did not attend the devops or ruby portions, but it has been said by some that they were not as exceptional.</p>

<p>Thanks to the organizers for selecting great content and presenters.  Thank you to all the speakers for preparing some killer talks.</p>

<h2>Topics</h2>

<p>The mix of topics seemed relevant and varied.  This was welcome.  There was just a bit of overlap on some topics.  Conference organizers put similar topics together, which was fine.  But in one case, the back-to-back speakers, from the same company and essentially the same topic had so much overlap that it was obvious.  Repetition is good, but it should be done in front of the YouTube recording of a single, great talk on the subject.  The conference was recorded, so hopefully we can see the sessions online soon.</p>

<h2>Venue</h2>

<p>The conference met at the Salt Lake City Public Library.  It's a great city.  It's a cool building.  It has a location close to public transit lines.  The stadium seating in the conference room is good for visibility but bad for knees.  There were plenty of power sources.</p>

<p>Despite these good points about the location, I found myself not super-excited about showing up at the library for another conference.  I feel like it's time for something fresh.</p>

<h2>Swag</h2>

<p>There was a nice shirt with mysterious symbols emblazened across the front.  Ruby was discernable.  I'm still up in the air over which represents JavaScript or devops.  There was also a nice, laminate sticker that they gave out with the conference logo.  Sponsors gave out nothing.  I was hoping for an O.C. Tanner gold bracelet and Instructure panda hoodie.  There was also a stunning lack of sweet treats and lunch. :(  In the place of actual food, there was an especially long, 2-hour lunch break -- oh, and a lot of water.</p>

<h2>I'd Go Again</h2>

<p>I'd definitely go again if the speaker and topic lineup seemed as promising as it turned out to be this year.  Next year, hopefully I'll attend at a different location in Salt Lake City and enjoy a chocolate eclair whilst learning about how I can actually use es6 features in the then-current evergreen browsers.</p>

<h2>My Notes</h2>

<p>As I've indicated, there were many topics touched upon that were interesting and helpful.  I've included my chicken scratch below (if you can actually type chicken scratch), mostly so you can grab some hyperlinks if you'd like.</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>react.js - Pete Hunt - made react look very interesting from a perspective of the underlying ideas</p>

<pre><code> - jsx - http://facebook.github.io/react/docs/jsx-in-depth.html
 - virtual dom
 - simplicity over familiarity
  - riot.js - super-small mvp lib - https://moot.it/riotjs/docs/
</code></pre>

<p>macros - James Long -</p>

<pre><code> - sweet.js
</code></pre>

<p>async js - Jafar Husain - simplicity of event handling, handling of race conditions, and description of handling looked very compelling</p>

<pre><code> - observable - combine iterator (‘i’m done’) with event (pub sub)
 - events are just arrays
 - vector programming - transformations over collections
 - practice and learn - http://jhusain.github.io/learnrx/
</code></pre>

<p>async -</p>

<pre><code> - same bit as above
 - rxjs - http://reactive-extensions.github.io/RxJS/ - https://rx.codeplex.com/
 - Reactive Manifesto - http://www.reactivemanifesto.org/
</code></pre>

<p>ball of mud - Brandon Hays - most entertaining; great</p>

<pre><code> - Ball of mud architecture - http://laputan.org/mud/
 - @tehviking
</code></pre>

<p>TDD ember - Andy Pliszka</p>

<p>Screenreaders - Ryan Florence - a humanistic appeal to do the right thing and help those with disabilities on the web</p>

<pre><code> - aria-role
</code></pre>

<p>seo - Jeff Whepley</p>

<pre><code> - fragment spec
 - make server render substates, js can pick up
</code></pre>

<p>teach kids js - Liz Abinante - fun and light encouragement to share programming concepts with children</p>

<pre><code> - children are moldable
 - creative, imagination
 - not limited by inhibitions
 - start early, have time for mastery by young age.
</code></pre>

<p>modules, packages - Guy Bedford</p>

<pre><code> - traceur - still use
 - es6-module-loader - es6 loader polyfill - used by addy osmani’s todomvc - http://addyosmani.github.io/todomvc-backbone-es6/
 - systemjs - shim require on top of es6 loader polyfill
 - jspm.io + systemjs - https://github.com/systemjs
 - addy osmani’s todomvc rewrite experience - http://blog.tastejs.com/rewriting-a-webapp-with-ecmascript-6
</code></pre>

<p>web animation - Jeremy Kahn</p>

<pre><code> - detect end of css animation - http://blog.teamtreehouse.com/using-jquery-to-detect-when-css3-animations-and-transitions-end
 - edit keyframe animation via js - https://github.com/jlongster/css-animations.js
 - js tweening - https://github.com/jeremyckahn/shifty/
 - stylie - viz tool create keyframe animation
</code></pre>

<p>hardware hack - Jamisson Dance</p>

<pre><code> - npm - johnny-five - node arduino
 - npm - xbox-controller
 - parrot ar drone
      - “That’s against the spirit of node to use something when you could rewrite it yourself.”
 - arduino uno w/ breadboard - ~$100
</code></pre>

<p>flight.js - Kassandra Perch</p>

<pre><code> - slides - http://kperch.github.io/mtn_west/
</code></pre>

<p>node error handling - Jamund Ferguson</p>

<pre><code> - Kraken - on top of express - https://github.com/paypal/kraken-js
 - try/catch - for json.parse
 - callback - first param is err
 - custom error - custom name, attach custom data (e.g., ServerError has a list of services hitting, ports, etc)
 - process.on(‘uncaughtException’) must always process.exit()
 - handle errors in middleware - call next w/ error as first param, call return right after
 - use default error handler in express - app.use(function (err, req, res, next) { res.send(500, etc) })
 - node core notes - https://nodefirm.hackpad.com/Node-Error-Handling-Summit-uXFi4FUg8Td
</code></pre>

<p>client error handling - Todd Gardner</p>

<pre><code> - error handling service - http://trackjs.com/
 - name your inner functions
 - stacktrace.js - normalizes format of stack trace
 - tracekit.js - get stack traces in old browsers
 - zone.js - long stack traces across async events
</code></pre>

<p>gulp - Eric Schoffstall</p>

<pre><code> - getfractal
 - still has problems with 3rd-party file-based builds, such as require.js
 - github.com/substack/stream-handbook
</code></pre>

<p>canvas animation - Josh Robertson</p>

<p>```</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ng-Conf Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/ng-conf-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T07:22:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/ng-conf-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ng-Conf just happened last week in Salt Lake City, Utah.  It was awesome.  Oh blast, I blew the punch line.  Anyway, here's my take.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/4swtO6x.jpg" alt="ng-conf" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Format</h2>

<p>Two days.  Early 'til late.  One track.  20-40 min talks virtually back to back.  Lightning'y?  When we broke for lunch, I felt relieved.  My brain could go into some low-power mode.  Breaks between talks were mostly announced as anywhere from 30 seconds to 3 minutes, this whilst yammering off a short list of swag winners.  The format encouraged content, and there was a lot of it!</p>

<h2>Line Up</h2>

<p>The conference was easy to look forward to.  Looking at the speaker list, I was immediately impressed.  At one point during the event, Aaron Frost said that they hoped if the Angular team would come that they'd get more attendees.  Yes, that was a draw.  It was fun having them there.  Core.  Very core.  I believe that about each member of the team took the stage over the two days.</p>

<p>The speaker list in total was very impressive.  There was a good mix of local and remote talent who came together to cover a broad array of Angular and JavaScript-related topics.</p>

<h2>Talk Quality</h2>

<p>Talk for talk, just numbers-wise, it was definitely one of the most high quality conferences I've attended.  Of course, there were some less-than-stellar presentations.  But, on the whole, I was more than impressed by the subject mastery and teaching ability of the speakers.  Thank you to everyone who prepared.</p>

<p>There were also some definite highlights: Dave Smith on directives, Vojta Jina on DI, Brian Ford on zone.js, and Julie Ralph on Protractor.</p>

<p>And one of the best parts is that each of these talks was recorded on video for a livestream and <a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/ngconfvideos">on youtube for later viewing</a>.</p>

<h2>Venue</h2>

<p>The conference was held at the Little America hotel in Salt Lake City.  It was a beautiful location.  The combined main ballrooms that the talks were held in were awesome.  Plenty of marble.  The food was great.  There weren't tons of snacks, but that was probably good for my health.  The air quality in Salt Lake during the conference wasn't good.  In fact, oobleck!  But, I didn't get food poisoning -- plus!</p>

<h2>Smooth</h2>

<p>I heard it said by multiple people during the conference that it was the best first-time conference they had attended.  Indeed, everything went Domo smooth.  The content was the star.  It was fun.  It was energetic (minus some confusing lack of screaming for all the sweet swag -- probably had something to do with the sheer amount, like clapping for the 3rd curtain call).  The AV crew did a fantastic job.  Usually, it's annoying to sit in an audience as video or audio problems plague the start of a talk.  That simply did not happen here, and it was oh, so refreshing.</p>

<p>Oh yeah, and sweet jacket!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[UtahJS Conf 2013 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/utahjs-conf-2013-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-20T06:59:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/utahjs-conf-2013-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/G3BBShC.png" alt="UtahJS" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Schedule</h2>

<p>The conference covered a single day.  Keynote in the morning by Tom Dale, co-creator of Emberjs.  3 tracks thereafter with 5 talks each.  There was a specialized track, all focused on Angular, which was nice for anyone that wanted to focus on that framework.  There was less Node focus overall compared to last year, which was disappointing.  There were 3 talks focused on testing.  We need more good testing talks.</p>

<p>My impression on the talks overall was that they were well done and that the speakers were generally engaging.  The topics focused a little much on browser-side MV* frameworks, but I guess that's hot right now.  Every talk I went to was meant for beginners at a very introductory level.  That was disappointing.  Of the topics presented, I found myself surprisingly most interested in Emberjs.  I have been tinkering with it since then and need to build something with it.</p>

<h2>The Food</h2>

<p>There was a plentitude of simple carbohydrates ready to serve to all learners at all times.  That was awesome.  Pastries appeared for breakfast, un-advertised.  They didn't do a boxed lunch this year.  Some didn't cry.  I almost did.  But I was pointed to a great gryo at a nearby Greek eatery instead.  Apparently the host venue, the Salt Lake City Public Library, didn't approve of serving food.  This, I don't understand, given that there was plenty of food floating around.  Apparenly pastries are ok, and sandwiches are not.</p>

<h2>The People</h2>

<p>Always a fun flavor to a conference, the attendees were great to mingle with.  The JavaScript community is a fun group to be with.  In Utah, we're a fairly small, tight group.  It was fun to have Tom Dale show up.  It was even said by some that the Ember folks were "actually nice" as opposed to what was thought to be observed by some on Twitter.  Haha.  I smiled quite a bit when I heard that.</p>

<h2>The Afterparty</h2>

<p>The party was put on by O.C. Tanner and Domo.  O.C. Tanner is my current home base.  We were in charge of prepping the space.  It was like a classic text adventure trying to guide party-comers through the labyrinth of the O.C. Tanner building to the eventual pot of gold that was the party.</p>

<p>The food never stopped coming, even after my stomach had taken on its full capacity.  Marvelous Catering (gotta love that name) provided a delicious "luau pork dinner".  I heard "luau" and assumed pineapple, of which there was none, which disappointed me just a little.  The owner of Fongo Bongo, a local game shop supplied a great collection of board and card games.  We had a couple Xboxen humming whilst TVs blasted fighting games to which I knew no combos.  We had a great time.</p>

<h2>Next Year</h2>

<p>I'm glad that this event has shown some perpetuity.  I hope it continues next year.  I think they have a good formula.  The price, the locale, the speaker lineup, and the associated activities make for a good one-day experience each Spring.  I would focus on improving one bit next year: the website.  It was the least well-done part of the conference.  I find that extremely ironic given the target market for the event.</p>

<p>So next Spring, come to Utah and attend the JsConf.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mountain West Ruby Conf 2013 Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/mountain-west-ruby-conf-2013-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T15:23:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/mountain-west-ruby-conf-2013-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently attended the Mountain West Ruby Conference.  It was my first time going.  I was pleasantly surprised by the quality of the conference.  I would recommend it.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/ABNr5MC.jpg" alt="Mountain West Ruby Conf" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Peeps</h2>

<p>I'm new to the Ruby community.  I get to use it more in my current job than I ever have before.  Whenever entering a new community, it's good to find some friends.  I was pleased to notice that everyone I encountered at the conference was very friendly and welcoming.</p>

<p>About the coolest thing about the community is one of the slogans: MINSWAN, which means "Matz is nice, so we are nice."  How cool is that?  Matz is the Ruby creator.  Wait, who am I kidding.  You already know that.</p>

<p>I was very impressed with the blatant lack of trolling other communities.  This even with the live stream video cameras rolling (people can tend to do weird things when put on camera).</p>

<p>The conference attracted speakers and attendees from as far away as Australia.</p>

<h2>Speakers</h2>

<p>I didn't look too closely at the schedule previous to attending.  Once I got there, I was surprised at the caliber of those people and companies who were represented.  These were big names in the tech community, such as Matz, himself, Github, Heroku, and others.</p>

<p>The conference is single track, so that meant I got to see everyone speak.  I mostly like that but kind of hate that.  I believe it also meant fewer speaking slots, so everyone was pretty top notch.</p>

<p>I was impressed with the stage presence of most speakers.  A few were pretty droning, but in general everyone was very polished, had good slide decks, and shared engaging and useful content.</p>

<p>Devops was the stated subject matter of an entire day of the conference.  This was cool.  We can use that kind of focus on the subject.  But then it bled into the next days as well.  I want some pure code, pure Ruby'ness.  I got some of that, but not as much as I would like.  I paid my devops dues the first day.  I was ready to not hear any more of it on days 2 and 3.</p>

<h2>Venue</h2>

<p>It was in my back yard!  I loved the lack of a hotel requirement!  Apparently some visitors even camped in the wilderness, Nacho style.</p>

<p>The Salt Lake City Public Library is a great downtown location for a small conference.  In this case, with the conference being single track, the single largest room, the amphitheatre, was the only room required for all attendees.  It featured plenty of seating -- at the cost of no leg room.</p>

<p>The wifi also held up better than it has for similar gatherings in this space.  It was announced that "the city and Xmission are working feverishly" to maintain connectivity several times over the 3 days.  It still didn't stay up.  This is a common tech conf occurrence.</p>

<p>I was sorely disappointed with the lack of sugary confections meant to encourage the jollyness and attentiveness of the conference-goers.  At one point, it was necessary to slip out and find a good bakery downtown.  I was not disappointed.  I was happy to see at least the vendors' vinyl stickers come out on the last day.  We need more of that!</p>

<p>In all, it was a good use of my couple days.  It wasn't too pricey, but then, I wasn't paying.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SORT Conf 2012]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/sort-conf-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-10T16:57:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/sort-conf-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The sky lightens with the rising sun.  Wheels are on the road.  Friends are in the car.  The leaves are changing on the towering Wasatch mountains.  Finally, we pull up to the University of Utah Institute building.  Stepping out of the car, the October air is fresh and clear, high in the Rockies.  It's a good day for a tech conference.  It's a good day for SORT.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/q1cr5.jpg" alt="Wasatch mountains" />
http://flic.kr/p/bDP2fF</p>

<!--more-->


<p>SORT is an annual tech conference put on by the LDS Church.  The IT shops of the Church are all represented, including ICS, Family Search, the BYUs, CES, and probably a couple more.  Attendance last year, I think, was about 1200.</p>

<h2>Something For Everyone</h2>

<p>A unique feature of the conference is that there are soooo many subjects covered.  It's really kind of a joke the number of tracks that are represented:</p>

<ol>
<li>EIM</li>
<li>Architecture</li>
<li>Design</li>
<li>Engineering</li>
<li>Partner Summit</li>
<li>Infrastructure</li>
<li>Leadership</li>
<li>PM</li>
<li>QA</li>
<li>Requirements</li>
<li>Security</li>
<li>Sharepoint/CRM</li>
<li>Solution Mgmt</li>
<li>Other (misc)</li>
</ol>


<p>Holy cow!  That's a little nuts.  It started out as an engineering-only conference in 2009.  Since then, it's blossomed.  I feel like it has been a double-edged sword:  The whole office is invited and should have something to soak up there, but it feels like the engineering track has been watered down a bit.</p>

<h2>Mostly Intro</h2>

<p>The topics are varied.  It's often the case that there's so much going on that you don't know what to pick for each hour.  That is awesome!  Out of the presentations offered in the engineering track, I would love to see more intermediate or advanced topics.  More deep dives would be fun to geek out about.  I think we touch that in some cases, but in general, I feel that the presentations could be categorized as cursory introductions to topics.</p>

<h2>Free-flowing Sugar</h2>

<p>I am never lacking for ATP at SORT.  The day starts with a great breakfast.  Lunch is also delicious.  This year, both were provided by Kneaders bakery.  Between every session, there are plentiful mounds of various snack foods and refreshing beverages.  And being a conference put on by the Church, the drinks are top notch, ready for the Church membership. :)</p>

<h2>Entry to Speaking</h2>

<p>I have presented at SORT for each of the last 4 years.  You already know the bar can't be that high.  If you submit a paper, you'll probably be accepted.  I was 2 for 3 this year. :)  Some might worry that this would lower the quality of the conference material and presentation.  Yes, it probably does.  But, just like any conference, if you are a little careful in your schedule selection, you'll find some fantastic speakers and super-compelling content.</p>

<h2>A Yearly Highlight</h2>

<p>In all, SORT is a fantastic experience.  I look forward to it next year.  It's fun to review what I've learned and presented on in the past (Django, then jQuery plugins, then TDD on MarkLogic, this year BackboneJs).</p>

<p>It's at a great, close location.  The company is fantastic.  The topics are varied and interesting.  The two days are time well-spent to me.  I feel tired (a sign of lots of fire hose drinking).  I'm inspired to learn a few new things:</p>

<ol>
<li>Do more CoffeeScript</li>
<li>Try SocketStream</li>
<li>Use Postgres' row_to_json</li>
<li>Try LawnChair and IndexDb</li>
<li>Do some user media capture</li>
</ol>


<p>Did any of you go this year?  What do you appreciate the most about SORT or your most recent conference?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
