<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: react | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/react/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-03T08:11:00-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Test React componentWillReceiveProps]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/test-react-componentwillreceiveprops/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-26T08:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/test-react-componentwillreceiveprops</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Testing React Components has been easier and more enjoyable than any previous UI unit testing I've done in the past.  Components that have interesting things happen in lifecycle methods have a little more setup to get tested.  Components that use the <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> method are in this category.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DXuSNbw.png" alt="react" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>React Test Setup</h2>

<p>Not all lifecycle methods require as much setup in a test as <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code>.  This is because:</p>

<ul>
<li>This method is concerned with <strong><em>changing</em></strong> props.</li>
<li>Changing props directly on a React Component (even under test) is against the React code of conduct</li>
</ul>


<p>So, we need something that is legal to change... <code>state</code>!  We need to not modify our subject under test and simply pass it new <code>props</code>.</p>

<p>My solution is to create a React Component specifically for the test.  This Component will be a parent to the subject under test, on which we can set <code>state</code>.  We'll design it so that this state is transferred to the child Component under test.</p>

<h2>React Component using <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code></h2>

<p>You might have a React Component to test that looks like this:</p>

<p>```js
var ComponentToTest = React.createClass({
  getInitialProps() {</p>

<pre><code>return {
  myProp: "blank"
};
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  getInitialState() {</p>

<pre><code>return {
  modified: "still blank"
};
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  componentWillReceiveProps(nextProps) {</p>

<pre><code>this.setState({
  modified: nextProps.myProp + "IsSoModified"
});
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  render() {</p>

<pre><code>return &lt;div class="displayed"&gt;{this.state.modified}&lt;/div&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
});
```</p>

<p>There is nothing particularly interesting about this subject beyond the fact that it uses <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code>.  When new props are received, internal state is modified.  In real life, more interesting things like data fetching or complex calculations might be done here and then stored in state.  We simply are matching the scenario of needing to verify something when <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> is called.</p>

<h2>A Parent Test Component</h2>

<p>The test to exercise <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> on the above Component might look like this:</p>

<p>```js
var React = require("react/addons");
var TestUtils = React.addons.TestUtils;</p>

<p>it("displays a modified state upon changing props", function () {
  var TestParent = React.createFactory(React.createClass({</p>

<pre><code>getInitialState() {
  return { testState: "init" };
},
render() {
  return &lt;ComponentToTest ref="sot" myProp={this.state.testState} /&gt;
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }));</p>

<p>  var parent = TestUtils.renderIntoDocument(TestParent());
  parent.refs.sot.props.myProp.should.eql("init");</p>

<p>  parent.setState({</p>

<pre><code>testState: "somethingElse"
</code></pre>

<p>  });</p>

<p>  parent.refs.sot.props.myProp.should.eql("somethingElse");
  parent.refs.sot.state.modified.should.eql("somethingElseIsSoModified"); // assert #1
  var child = TestUtils.scryRenderedDOMComponentsWithClass(parent, "displayed")[0];
  child.getDOMNode().innerText.should.eql("somethingElseIsSoModified");  // assert #2
});
```</p>

<p>The <code>TestParent</code> component is created specifically for this test.  It renders the Component under test.  It sets a <code>ref</code> attribute to it for easy access.  Once we render the parent, the initial state was sent as the prop to the child Component.  As soon as we <code>setState</code> on the parent, a new prop is sent to the child, triggering <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code>.</p>

<p>Finally, I've included two assertion styles.  Again, there are going to be more interesting things that you're asserting here in real life.  In this case I'm verifying that state that renders directly to the UI is set in our lifecycle method.  I can interrogate the state directly.  Here, we reach into the child Component state for assertion method #1.  That may sound bad, but remember that <code>TestParent</code> was created only in the context of this test anyway, so the level we're reaching through to grab child state is just test code.  Assertion method #2 is to go to the DOM to verify final output from the state change.</p>

<p>There is definitely more setup here to make this happen.  I feel like usually testing a React Component doesn't require this much test code.</p>

<h2><code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> in Action</h2>

<p>Here is a Component that uses <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> to make a simple display change:</p>

<p><a class="jsbin-embed" href="http://jsbin.com/munaxuguta/12/embed?js,output">JS Bin</a><script src="http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js"></script></p>

<p>You can also check out this <a href="http://jsbin.com/buwoqod/22/edit?js,output">slightly modified jsbin</a> which does the test assertion.</p>

<p>What methods have you used to test Components that use either <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> or other interesting lifecycle methods?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Test React-Router Previous Params for Component Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/test-react-router-params-component-update/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-09T15:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/test-react-router-params-component-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Once upon a time, react-router transferred params and query params from the url via props into components.  It doesn't happen this way any more.  So, let's say you have a need in your component like overriding <code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> in your component which only has access to <code>this.props</code> and <code>this.state</code>.   How can you use the url data to affect the component re-render or not?</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DXuSNbw.png" alt="react" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Why control rendering with the url?</h2>

<p>There are two instances that come to mind when considering the scenarios that it might be needful to control the update of your component based on the url:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Avoid re-render</strong>: Of course, if the component we're talking about is a page-level component, you'll most likely always be wanting to re-render as the url changes.  But, if you're a little widget component that cares about the url, you might not need to always re-render on url change.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trigger re-render when it might not otherwise happen</strong>: For whatever reason, you may have already needed to implement <code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> in your component.  This function returns true or false to flag a "should" or "should not" re-render.  You'll need to access url state and likely previous url state in this method to make re-renders happen that otherwise wouldn't if you had no logic in this function for it.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Of course, beyond these re-render scenarios, there are many other situations in which knowing previous and current states in the url could come in handy.</p>

<h2>React-Router in shouldComponentUpdate</h2>

<p><code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> determines if component should re-render.  It's called whenever <code>this.props</code> or <code>this.state</code> changes.  It has access to incoming props and state via the function parameters.</p>

<p>React-router gives your component access to params and query params by requiring you to mix in the <code>State</code> param from react-router.  Then you have access to new functions, <code>this.getParams()</code> and <code>this.getQuery()</code>.  If you only need to know current url state, this is enough.  If you want to compare current url state to previous url state, you'll have to save the parts that you care about.  We'll do that in <code>this.state</code>.</p>

<p>Let's say that we want to trigger a redraw on changes to a <code>range</code> query parameter.  The component might, in part, look like this:</p>

<p>```
var { State } = require('react-router')</p>

<p>module.exports = React.createClass({</p>

<p>  mixins: [ State ],</p>

<p>  getInitialState() {</p>

<pre><code>range: nul
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentWillReceiveProps() {</p>

<pre><code>this.setState({
  range: this.getQuery().range
})
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentWillMount() {</p>

<pre><code>this.setState({
  range: this.getQuery().range
})
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  shouldComponentUpdate() {</p>

<pre><code>return this.state.range !== nextState.range
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  // ...</p>

<p>})
```</p>

<p>When the url params change, <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> is called.  But this is not called on the first render, thus we implement <code>componentWillMount</code>.  Both these functions save the <code>range</code> from the url to the component state.  Now, as <code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> is called on future <code>this.props</code> and <code>this.state</code> changes, current and next <code>range</code> values can be compared and used in "should re-render" calculation.</p>

<p>What other ways have you found to accomplish this tracking of previous state in the url?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[React-Router with Flux]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/react-router-with-flux/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T09:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/react-router-with-flux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>react-router provides great route handling with route params and query params.  Flux provides a pattern for building React apps, including a pattern from providing data to your components.  Here's a straightforward way to make route changes trigger data changes in your components.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DXuSNbw.png" alt="react" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Note: Code here reflects usage of react-router 0.11.x.</p>

<p>It is often the case that we'll need to trigger data changes in a react component in our Flux app because of a route transition.  A prime example of this would be on an object show page, where the details of a particular object are being shown.  In our example, let's say that we're showing the details of a book, such as title, author, and description.</p>

<p>The route to our book detail page is likely defined as:</p>

<p><code>js routes.js
// ...
&lt;Route name="book" path="/books/:id" handler={require('./books-show')} /&gt;
</code></p>

<p>The handler is just a controller-component that defines the view.  It might look simply like:</p>

<p>```js books-show.js
const React = require('react')
const {State} = require('react-router')</p>

<p>const BooksStore = require('./books-store')</p>

<p>module.exports = React.createClass({</p>

<p>  displayName: 'BooksShow',</p>

<p>  mixins: [ State ],</p>

<p>  getInitialState() {</p>

<pre><code>return this.getStateFromStores()
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  getStateFromStores() {</p>

<pre><code>return {
  book: BooksStore.find({ id: this.getParams().id })
}
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentDidMount() {</p>

<pre><code>BooksStore.addChangeListener(this._onChange)
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentWillUnmount() {</p>

<pre><code>BooksStore.removeChangeListener(this._onChange)
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  _onChange: function() {</p>

<pre><code>this.setState(this.getStateFromStores())
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  render() {</p>

<pre><code>return (
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;{this.state.book.title}&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;{this.state.book.author}&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;{this.state.book.description}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
)
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>})
```</p>

<p>Note that the view component references a <code>BooksStore</code> for getting its initial state.  The state of <code>book</code> will also be updated as the <code>BooksStore</code> emits that its data has changed and <code>this._onChange</code> is called.</p>

<p>Every time a route transitions, react-router has a <code>Router.run</code> callback that will also run in order to render the matching route.  This will also be a great place to put our action to signal to our Flux app that routes are transitioning and therefore other stuff like data in the display might need to change as well.</p>

<p><code>js
Router.run(routes, (Handler, state) =&gt; {
  React.render(&lt;Handler /&gt;, document.body)
  BooksAction.transition(state.params)
})
</code></p>

<p><strong>Important note</strong>: Make sure the transition action is called after <code>React.render</code> so that the change emission will be detected after render, otherwise you'll be one route transition behind.</p>

<p>The <code>BooksAction.transition</code> definition is something very simple -- something that can trigger events on the dispatcher:</p>

<p>```js books-actions.js
exports.transition = () => {
  AppDispatcher.handleViewAction({</p>

<pre><code>type: ActionTypes.TRANSITION
</code></pre>

<p>  })
}
```</p>

<p>The final connection is in the store, where the dispatched action can be listened for an then trigger the store event, updating the component views:</p>

<p>```js books-store.js
var BooksStore = merge(EventEmitter.prototype, {
  find(filter) {</p>

<pre><code>// ...
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})</p>

<p>BooksStore.dispatchToken = AppDispatcher.register((payload) => {
  var action = payload.action
  switch(action.type) {</p>

<pre><code>// ...

case ActionTypes.TRANSITION:
  BooksStore.emitChange()
  break
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})</p>

<p>module.exports = BooksStore</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>At this point, all the route transitions should trigger data changes in views.  Visiting the url <code>/books/1</code> and then the url <code>/books/2</code> should display different data on screen according to which book id was in the route.  <code>Router.Link</code> should work correctly, usable instead of buttons with actions being triggered on click.</p>

<p>react-router and Flux make for a great combo in this way, right?  What adjustments would you make?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Send Props to Children in React]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/send-props-to-children-react/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-12T16:55:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/send-props-to-children-react</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In React, you're always making components.  Sometimes components are standalone.  Other times, you'll have components that can nest children components.  Sometimes you'll want to send properties to the children components from the parent as often as a doting parent wants to send packages to a child missionary.  It's possible, it's simple, and it's not documented super well.  Here's one method.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DXuSNbw.png" alt="React" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Children Components</h2>

<p>When parent components are rendered, they have access to a special property, <code>this.props.children</code>.  It's like an Angular <code>ng-transclude</code> or an Ember <code>yield</code>.  Children components are generally rendered something like this:</p>

<p>```js
React.createClass({
  render: function () {</p>

<pre><code>return (
  &lt;div id="iAmParentHearMeRoar"&gt;
    {this.props.children}
  &lt;/div&gt;
)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})
```</p>

<p>The generic example above shows simply how to render children, <code>props</code> untouched, within a parent component.  Sometimes, however, a parent wants to bequeath its children with extra properties.  How will we make that happen?</p>

<h2>Setting Child Props</h2>

<p><code>props</code> are meant to be immutable.  But, in order for us to send <code>props</code> values to our children, we're going to essentially loop through our children and set props on them as a part of our parent <code>render</code> function.</p>

<p>Deep breath.  It's ok.  The children that we'll loop through aren't mounted component instances.  They are, instead, <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/blog/2014/07/17/react-v0.11.html#descriptors">descriptors</a>.  These descriptors have all the <code>props</code> attributes that we've declared should be put on the components, but they haven't been rendered yet.  Because of this, we can change props, and it's ok.  We're not mutating what has rendered.  The data still hasn't flowed to the children.  We're still effectively still riffing on the logic of what the children components should really be when they're eventually mounted.</p>

<h2>Looping on Children Components</h2>

<p><code>this.props.children</code> is a funny property.  It's special in more ways than one.  The things that might trip us up in looping is that even though it sounds like a plural thing, meaning an array, sometimes it's a singular object.  To help avoid potential problems, React gives us a helper, <code>React.Children</code>.  It has a few functions for array iteration, such as <code>map</code> and <code>forEach</code> that help account for the potential forms of <code>this.props.children</code>.</p>

<h2>Functional Modifications</h2>

<p>Immutable data is a big part of functional programming.  This means that when we 'mutate' the props, we want to mutate on a clone of the child component without affecting the original.  There's an input, there's an output, and the input is untouched.  Once we have our cloned children components as we want them, we'll render those instead.  React offers another great helper for cloning components and setting properties in a single function, <code>React.addons.cloneWithProps</code>.  Note that in order to use this function, you need to <code>require('react/addons')</code>.</p>

<h2>Checking Child Type</h2>

<p>It's a generally-useful thing to be able to tell what the React class type of a component object is.  It's an applicable skill in terms of looping through child components because we might not want to modify the properties of all types of children.  Each React component class has a <code>type</code> attribute accessible via <code>MyComponent.type</code>.  This attribute is also available on component descriptors.</p>

<h2>A Child CheckOption Example</h2>

<p>To bring this all together and illustrate the concepts, let's say we created a <code>RadioGroup</code> component that could take one or many <code>RadioOption</code> child components.  In raw html, which is what our component will eventually render, <code>input</code>s with type <code>checkbox</code> need to all have the same <code>name</code> attribute value to work well as toggles within the group.  But this is something that React can help us not have to duplicate.  We'll instead put a <code>name</code> property on the parent <code>RadioGroup</code> and have it transfer it as a property on all its children.  The implementation might look like this:</p>

<p>```js
/<em>* @jsx React.DOM </em>/</p>

<p>var React = require('react/addons')</p>

<p>var RadioOption = React.createClass({
  render: function () {</p>

<pre><code>return (
  &lt;label&gt;
    &lt;input type="radio" value={this.props.value} name={this.props.name} /&gt;
    {this.props.label}
  &lt;/label&gt;
)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})</p>

<p>var RadioGroup = React.createClass({
  renderChildren: function () {</p>

<pre><code>return React.Children.map(this.props.children, function (child) {
  if (child.type === RadioOption.type)
    return React.addons.cloneWithProps(child, {
      name: this.props.name
    })
  else
    return child
}.bind(this))
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  render: function () {</p>

<pre><code>return (
  &lt;div class="radio-group"&gt;
    {this.renderChildren()}
  &lt;/div&gt;
)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})</p>

<p>var WhereImUsingRadioGroups = React.createClass({
  render: function () {</p>

<pre><code>return (
  &lt;RadioGroup name="blizzard-games"&gt;
    &lt;RadioOption label="Warcraft 2" value="wc2" /&gt;
    &lt;RadioOption label="Warcraft 3" value="wc3" /&gt;
    &lt;RadioOption label="Starcraft 1" value="sc1" /&gt;
    &lt;RadioOption label="Starcraft 2" value="sc2" /&gt;
  &lt;/RadioGroup&gt;
)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})
```</p>

<p>In this example, where the parent <code>RadioGroup</code> has the <code>name</code> prop, it will be given to each of the children so their <code>name</code> prop will match and the radio group will work as expected.  Thus, the hearts of the children are turned toward their fathers.</p>

<p>Is there a better way to do this?  How have you been sending <code>props</code> to children?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Set State in Callbacks in React]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/set-state-in-callbacks-in-react/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-23T08:30:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/set-state-in-callbacks-in-react</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In React, you can setup components that fetch their own data and set their own state with that data.  Because of the async nature of data fetching, you’ll have to make sure to keep things cleaned up to avoid the error of trying to set state in an unmounted component.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DXuSNbw.png" alt="React" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p><strong>Updated</strong> for React 0.13.  See below</p>

<h2>React Components setState</h2>

<p>If a React component fetches its own data, it will usually do so in the <code>componentDidMount</code> method.  In the data request callback, it will set its own state via the <code>this.setState</code> method.  (<code>this.state</code> should be treated as immutable.)  State should only be set on mounted components, or those components that are inserted into the dom.</p>

<p>If you attempt to set state on an unmounted component, you'll get an error that looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
Uncaught Error: Invariant Violation: replaceState(...): Can only update a mounted or mounting component.
</code></p>

<p>Others have reported this variation:</p>

<p><code>
Invariant Violation: replaceState(...): Cannot update while unmounting component. This usually means you called setState() on an unmounted component.
</code></p>

<p>Both indicate that you're setting state on a component that is not mounted.  How should one avoid this?  In my case, <code>setState</code> was being called in a callback that was firing after the component that initially started the request had already been unmounted from the dom.  Here are the two ways I addressed the problem...</p>

<h2>Assure Component isMounted</h2>

<p>If the component is mounted, <code>setState</code> is a safe bet.  If it's not mounted, never do it.  If it's not mounted, you probably don't about the state at that point either.  So wrap your state setting in <code>this.isMounted()</code>:</p>

<p>```js
React.createClass({
  componentDidMount: function () {</p>

<pre><code>MyModel.find(function (err, data) {
  if (this.isMounted()) {
    this.setState({
      goodiesFrom: data
    })
  }
}.bind(this))
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  // ...
})
```</p>

<p>It feels a bit like a hack, but it makes the code safe.  Another option...</p>

<h2>Abort the Request</h2>

<p>My asynchronous action is a network request that, when finished, will call the callback function.  When the component unmounts, I can just throw away the request so the callback is never invoked.  To do this, we'll take advantage of another React lifecycle hook, <code>componentWillUnmount</code>:</p>

<p>```js my-component.js
React.createClass({
  componentDidMount: function () {</p>

<pre><code>this.req = MyModel.find(function (err, data) {
  this.setState({})
}.bind(this))
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  componentWillUnmount: function () {</p>

<pre><code>this.req.abort()
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  // ...
})
```</p>

<p>In my model, I'm using the <a href="https://github.com/visionmedia/superagent">superagent</a> library for network requests which provides an <a href="http://visionmedia.github.io/superagent/#aborting-requests">abort</a> method.</p>

<p>```js my-model.js
var request = require(‘superagent')
MyModel.prototype.find = function (done) {
  return request(‘modelUrl’)</p>

<pre><code>.end(function (err, data) {
  if (data) {
    done(err, data.body)
  }
})
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Also note that in my <code>end</code> function callback, I'm checking for the existence of data.  This is because when a request is aborted, data will come back as undefined.</p>

<p>My favored method for solving the problem is the latter request abort method.  It feels cleaner that we're relying on the lifecycle functions of the component to deal with cleanup, much like we would for <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/tips/dom-event-listeners.html">events</a>.  How have you dealt with this problem?</p>

<h2>Update: Using ES6 Classes</h2>

<p>With React 0.13, you can define your components using the ES6 <code>class</code> definition.  These classes conspicuously change behavior from the old style of <code>React.createClass</code> in several ways.  Here are a couple that are relevant here:</p>

<ul>
<li>There is no <code>isMounted()</code> method any more</li>
<li>There is no <code>getDOMNode()</code> method any more</li>
</ul>


<p><code>isMounted</code> is gone, awol, as far as I can tell, and <code>getDOMNode</code> has been moved to a utility function.</p>

<p>So, in order to get the DOM Node, you'd call it like this:</p>

<p><code>js
React.getDOMNode(this) // `this` would be my component
</code></p>

<p>It functions as before.</p>

<p>In order to check <code>isMounted</code>, you're on your own.  My basic implementation can be seen in the following <a href="http://jsbin.com/telopegaya/2/edit?js,output">jsbin</a>.  Frankly, it feels dirty.  <code>React.findDOMNode</code> will throw an exception if the component isn't mounted, so we are using exceptions for flow control.  Egh:</p>

<p>```js
var isMounted = (component) => {
  // exceptions for flow control :(
  try {</p>

<pre><code>React.findDOMNode(component);
return true;
</code></pre>

<p>  } catch (e) {</p>

<pre><code>// Error: Invariant Violation: Component (with keys: props,context,state,refs,_reactInternalInstance) contains `render` method but is not mounted in the DOM
return false;
</code></pre>

<p>  }
};
```</p>

<p>How it might still be used:</p>

<p><a class="jsbin-embed" href="http://jsbin.com/telopegaya/2/embed?js,output">JS Bin</a><script src="http://static.jsbin.com/js/embed.js"></script></p>

<p>This leaves me with the question of why <code>isMounted</code> was removed if it helps solve a potential problem.  Do we solve it in another way?  Does the core library do more for you?  You can verify for yourself in the jsbin above that if you remove the <code>isMounted</code> check, the old invariant error message is still logged.</p>

<p>Does anyone have a <em>good</em> <code>isMounted</code> solution?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
