<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: react-router | Jake Trent]]></title>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/blog/categories/react-router/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jaketrent.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-03-24T16:04:29-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jaketrent.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jake Trent]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Test React-Router Previous Params for Component Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/test-react-router-params-component-update/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-09T15:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/test-react-router-params-component-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Once upon a time, react-router transferred params and query params from the url via props into components.  It doesn't happen this way any more.  So, let's say you have a need in your component like overriding <code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> in your component which only has access to <code>this.props</code> and <code>this.state</code>.   How can you use the url data to affect the component re-render or not?</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DXuSNbw.png" alt="react" /></p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Why control rendering with the url?</h2>

<p>There are two instances that come to mind when considering the scenarios that it might be needful to control the update of your component based on the url:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Avoid re-render</strong>: Of course, if the component we're talking about is a page-level component, you'll most likely always be wanting to re-render as the url changes.  But, if you're a little widget component that cares about the url, you might not need to always re-render on url change.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Trigger re-render when it might not otherwise happen</strong>: For whatever reason, you may have already needed to implement <code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> in your component.  This function returns true or false to flag a "should" or "should not" re-render.  You'll need to access url state and likely previous url state in this method to make re-renders happen that otherwise wouldn't if you had no logic in this function for it.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Of course, beyond these re-render scenarios, there are many other situations in which knowing previous and current states in the url could come in handy.</p>

<h2>React-Router in shouldComponentUpdate</h2>

<p><code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> determines if component should re-render.  It's called whenever <code>this.props</code> or <code>this.state</code> changes.  It has access to incoming props and state via the function parameters.</p>

<p>React-router gives your component access to params and query params by requiring you to mix in the <code>State</code> param from react-router.  Then you have access to new functions, <code>this.getParams()</code> and <code>this.getQuery()</code>.  If you only need to know current url state, this is enough.  If you want to compare current url state to previous url state, you'll have to save the parts that you care about.  We'll do that in <code>this.state</code>.</p>

<p>Let's say that we want to trigger a redraw on changes to a <code>range</code> query parameter.  The component might, in part, look like this:</p>

<p>```
var { State } = require('react-router')</p>

<p>module.exports = React.createClass({</p>

<p>  mixins: [ State ],</p>

<p>  getInitialState() {</p>

<pre><code>range: nul
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentWillReceiveProps() {</p>

<pre><code>this.setState({
  range: this.getQuery().range
})
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentWillMount() {</p>

<pre><code>this.setState({
  range: this.getQuery().range
})
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  shouldComponentUpdate() {</p>

<pre><code>return this.state.range !== nextState.range
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  // ...</p>

<p>})
```</p>

<p>When the url params change, <code>componentWillReceiveProps</code> is called.  But this is not called on the first render, thus we implement <code>componentWillMount</code>.  Both these functions save the <code>range</code> from the url to the component state.  Now, as <code>shouldComponentUpdate</code> is called on future <code>this.props</code> and <code>this.state</code> changes, current and next <code>range</code> values can be compared and used in "should re-render" calculation.</p>

<p>What other ways have you found to accomplish this tracking of previous state in the url?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[React-Router with Flux]]></title>
    <link href="http://jaketrent.com/post/react-router-with-flux/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T09:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://jaketrent.com/post/react-router-with-flux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>react-router provides great route handling with route params and query params.  Flux provides a pattern for building React apps, including a pattern from providing data to your components.  Here's a straightforward way to make route changes trigger data changes in your components.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/DXuSNbw.png" alt="react" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Note: Code here reflects usage of react-router 0.11.x.</p>

<p>It is often the case that we'll need to trigger data changes in a react component in our Flux app because of a route transition.  A prime example of this would be on an object show page, where the details of a particular object are being shown.  In our example, let's say that we're showing the details of a book, such as title, author, and description.</p>

<p>The route to our book detail page is likely defined as:</p>

<p><code>js routes.js
// ...
&lt;Route name="book" path="/books/:id" handler={require('./books-show')} /&gt;
</code></p>

<p>The handler is just a controller-component that defines the view.  It might look simply like:</p>

<p>```js books-show.js
const React = require('react')
const {State} = require('react-router')</p>

<p>const BooksStore = require('./books-store')</p>

<p>module.exports = React.createClass({</p>

<p>  displayName: 'BooksShow',</p>

<p>  mixins: [ State ],</p>

<p>  getInitialState() {</p>

<pre><code>return this.getStateFromStores()
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  getStateFromStores() {</p>

<pre><code>return {
  book: BooksStore.find({ id: this.getParams().id })
}
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentDidMount() {</p>

<pre><code>BooksStore.addChangeListener(this._onChange)
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  componentWillUnmount() {</p>

<pre><code>BooksStore.removeChangeListener(this._onChange)
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  _onChange: function() {</p>

<pre><code>this.setState(this.getStateFromStores())
</code></pre>

<p>  },</p>

<p>  render() {</p>

<pre><code>return (
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;{this.state.book.title}&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;{this.state.book.author}&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;{this.state.book.description}&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
)
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>})
```</p>

<p>Note that the view component references a <code>BooksStore</code> for getting its initial state.  The state of <code>book</code> will also be updated as the <code>BooksStore</code> emits that its data has changed and <code>this._onChange</code> is called.</p>

<p>Every time a route transitions, react-router has a <code>Router.run</code> callback that will also run in order to render the matching route.  This will also be a great place to put our action to signal to our Flux app that routes are transitioning and therefore other stuff like data in the display might need to change as well.</p>

<p><code>js
Router.run(routes, (Handler, state) =&gt; {
  React.render(&lt;Handler /&gt;, document.body)
  BooksAction.transition(state.params)
})
</code></p>

<p><strong>Important note</strong>: Make sure the transition action is called after <code>React.render</code> so that the change emission will be detected after render, otherwise you'll be one route transition behind.</p>

<p>The <code>BooksAction.transition</code> definition is something very simple -- something that can trigger events on the dispatcher:</p>

<p>```js books-actions.js
exports.transition = () => {
  AppDispatcher.handleViewAction({</p>

<pre><code>type: ActionTypes.TRANSITION
</code></pre>

<p>  })
}
```</p>

<p>The final connection is in the store, where the dispatched action can be listened for an then trigger the store event, updating the component views:</p>

<p>```js books-store.js
var BooksStore = merge(EventEmitter.prototype, {
  find(filter) {</p>

<pre><code>// ...
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})</p>

<p>BooksStore.dispatchToken = AppDispatcher.register((payload) => {
  var action = payload.action
  switch(action.type) {</p>

<pre><code>// ...

case ActionTypes.TRANSITION:
  BooksStore.emitChange()
  break
</code></pre>

<p>  }
})</p>

<p>module.exports = BooksStore</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>At this point, all the route transitions should trigger data changes in views.  Visiting the url <code>/books/1</code> and then the url <code>/books/2</code> should display different data on screen according to which book id was in the route.  <code>Router.Link</code> should work correctly, usable instead of buttons with actions being triggered on click.</p>

<p>react-router and Flux make for a great combo in this way, right?  What adjustments would you make?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
